<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ns0:uscDoc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:ns0="http://xml.house.gov/schemas/uslm/1.0" xmlns:ns3="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://xml.house.gov/schemas/uslm/1.0 USLM-1.0.15.xsd" xml:lang="en" identifier="/us/usc/t26">
  <ns0:meta>
    <dc:title>Title 26</dc:title>
    <dc:type>USCTitle</dc:type>
    <ns0:docNumber>26</ns0:docNumber>
    <ns0:docPublicationName>Online@119-100</ns0:docPublicationName>
    <ns0:property role="is-positive-law">no</ns0:property>
    <dc:publisher>OLRC</dc:publisher>
    <ns3:created>2026-04-17T11:14:53</ns3:created>
    <dc:creator>USCConverter 1.7.2</dc:creator>
  </ns0:meta>
  <ns0:title id="id4016a4d7-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26">
    <ns0:num value="26">Title 26—</ns0:num>
    <ns0:heading>INTERNAL REVENUE CODE</ns0:heading>
    <ns0:section style="-uslm-lc:I80" id="id45741684-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231">
      <ns0:num value="3231">§ 3231.</ns0:num>
      <ns0:heading> Definitions</ns0:heading>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id45741685-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/a">
        <ns0:num value="a" class="bold">(a)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Employer</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, the term “employer” means any carrier (as defined in subsection (g)), and any company which is directly or indirectly owned or controlled by one or more such carriers or under common control therewith, and which operates any equipment or facility or performs any service (except trucking service, casual service, and the casual operation of equipment or facilities) in connection with the transportation of passengers or property by railroad, or the receipt, delivery, elevation, transfer in transit, refrigeration or icing, storage, or handling of property transported by railroad, and any receiver, trustee, or other individual or body, judicial or otherwise, when in the possession of the property or operating all or any part of the business of any such employer; except that the term “employer” shall not include any street, interurban, or suburban electric railway, unless such railway is operating as a part of a general steam-railroad system of transportation, but shall not exclude any part of the general steam-railroad system of transportation now or hereafter operated by any other motive power. The Surface Transportation Board is hereby authorized and directed upon request of the Secretary, or upon complaint of any party interested, to determine after hearing whether any line operated by electric power falls within the terms of this exception. The term “employer” shall also include railroad associations, traffic associations, tariff bureaus, demurrage bureaus, weighing and inspection bureaus, collection agencies and other associations, bureaus, agencies, or organizations controlled and maintained wholly or principally by two or more employers as hereinbefore defined and engaged in the performance of services in connection with or incidental to railroad transportation; and railway labor organizations, national in scope, which have been or may be organized in accordance with the provisions of the Railway Labor Act, as amended (45 U.S.C., chapter 8), and their State and National legislative committees and their general committees and their insurance departments and their local lodges and divisions, established pursuant to the constitutions and bylaws of such organizations. The term “employer” shall not include any company by reason of its being engaged in the mining of coal, the supplying of coal to an employer where delivery is not beyond the mine tipple, and the operation of equipment or facilities therefor, or in any of such activities.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id45741686-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/b">
        <ns0:num value="b" class="bold">(b)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Employee</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, the term “employee” means any individual in the service of one or more employers for compensation. The term “employee” includes an officer of an employer. The term “employee” shall not include any individual while such individual is engaged in the physical operations consisting of the mining of coal, the preparation of coal, the handling (other than movement by rail with standard railroad locomotives) of coal not beyond the mine tipple, or the loading of coal at the tipple.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id45741687-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/c">
        <ns0:num value="c" class="bold">(c)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Employee representative</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, the term “employee representative” means any officer or official representative of a railway labor organization other than a labor organization included in the term “employer” as defined in subsection (a), who before or after <ns0:date date="1937-06-29">June 29, 1937</ns0:date>, was in the service of an employer as defined in subsection (a) and who is duly authorized and designated to represent employees in accordance with the Railway Labor Act (45 U.S.C., chapter 8), as amended, and any individual who is regularly assigned to or regularly employed by such officer or official representative in connection with the duties of his office.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id45741688-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d">
        <ns0:num value="d" class="bold">(d)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Service</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:chapeau style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, an individual is in the service of an employer whether his service is rendered within or without the United States, if—</ns0:chapeau>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id45741689-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/1">
          <ns0:num value="1">(1)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> he is subject to the continuing authority of the employer to supervise and direct the manner of rendition of his service, or he is rendering professional or technical services and is integrated into the staff of the employer, or he is rendering, on the property used in the employer’s operations, other personal services the rendition of which is integrated into the employer’s operations, and</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id4574168a-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/2">
          <ns0:num value="2">(2)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> he renders such service for compensation;</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:continuation style="-uslm-lc:I10" class="indent0 firstIndent0">except that an individual shall be deemed to be in the service of an employer, other than a local lodge or division or a general committee of a railway-labor-organization employer, not conducting the principal part of its business in the United States, only when he is rendering service to it in the United States; and an individual shall be deemed to be in the service of such a local lodge or division only if—</ns0:continuation>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id4574168b-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/3">
          <ns0:num value="3">(3)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> all, or substantially all, the individuals constituting its membership are employees of an employer conducting the principal part of its business in the United States; or</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id4574168c-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/4">
          <ns0:num value="4">(4)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> the headquarters of such local lodge or division is located in the United States;</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:continuation style="-uslm-lc:I10" class="indent0 firstIndent0">and an individual shall be deemed to be in the service of such a general committee only if—</ns0:continuation>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id4574168d-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/5">
          <ns0:num value="5">(5)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> he is representing a local lodge or division described in paragraph (3) or (4) immediately above; or</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id4574168e-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/6">
          <ns0:num value="6">(6)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> all, or substantially all, the individuals represented by it are employees of an employer conducting the principal part of its business in the United States; or</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id4574168f-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/d/7">
          <ns0:num value="7">(7)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> he acts in the capacity of a general chairman or an assistant general chairman of a general committee which represents individuals rendering service in the United States to an employer, but in such case if his office or headquarters is not located in the United States and the individuals represented by such general committee are employees of an employer not conducting the principal part of its business in the United States, only such proportion of the remuneration for such service shall be regarded as compensation as the proportion which the mileage in the United States under the jurisdiction of such general committee bears to the total mileage under its jurisdiction, unless such mileage formula is inapplicable, in which case such other formula as the Railroad Retirement Board may have prescribed pursuant to section 1(c) of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1937 (<ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s228a">45 U.S.C. 228a</ns0:ref>) shall be applicable, and if the application of such mileage formula, or such other formula as the Board may prescribe, would result in the compensation of the individual being less than 10 percent of his remuneration for such service, no part of such remuneration shall be regarded as compensation;</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:proviso style="-uslm-lc:I10" class="indent0 firstIndent0">
          <ns0:i>Provided however</ns0:i>, That an individual not a citizen or resident of the United States shall not be deemed to be in the service of an employer when rendering service outside the United States to an employer who is required under the laws applicable in the place where the service is rendered to employ therein, in whole or in part, citizens or residents thereof; and the laws applicable on <ns0:date date="1935-08-29">August 29, 1935</ns0:date>, in the place where the service is rendered shall be deemed to have been applicable there at all times prior to that date.</ns0:proviso>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id45741690-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e">
        <ns0:num value="e" class="bold">(e)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Compensation</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:chapeau style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter—</ns0:chapeau>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id45741691-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/1">
          <ns0:num value="1">(1)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> The term “compensation” means any form of money remuneration paid to an individual for services rendered as an employee to one or more employers. Such term does not include (i) the amount of any payment (including any amount paid by an employer for insurance or annuities, or into a fund, to provide for any such payment) made to, or on behalf of, an employee or any of his dependents under a plan or system established by an employer which makes provision for his employees generally (or for his employees generally and their dependents) or for a class or classes of his employees (or for a class or classes of his employees and their dependents), on account of sickness or accident disability or medical or hospitalization expenses in connection with sickness or accident disability or death, except that this clause does not apply to a payment for group-term life insurance to the extent that such payment is includible in the gross income of the employee, (ii) tips (except as is provided under paragraph (3)), (iii) an amount paid specifically—either as an advance, as reimbursement or allowance—for traveling or other bona fide and necessary expenses incurred or reasonably expected to be incurred in the business of the employer provided any such payment is identified by the employer either by a separate payment or by specifically indicating the separate amounts where both wages and expense reimbursement or allowance are combined in a single payment, or (iv) any remuneration which would not (if chapter 21 applied to such remuneration) be treated as wages (as defined in section 3121(a)) by reason of section 3121(a)(5). Such term does not include remuneration for service which is performed by a nonresident alien individual for the period he is temporarily present in the United States as a nonimmigrant under subparagraph (F), (J), (M), or (Q) of section 101(a)(15) of the Immigration and Nationality Act, as amended, and which is performed to carry out the purpose specified in subparagraph (F), (J), (M), or (Q), as the case may be. For the purpose of determining the amount of taxes under sections 3201 and 3221, compensation earned in the service of a local lodge or division of a railway-labor-organization employer shall be disregarded with respect to any calendar month if the amount thereof is less than $25. Compensation for service as a delegate to a national or international convention of a railway labor organization defined as an “employer” in subsection (a) of this section shall be disregarded for purposes of determining the amount of taxes due pursuant to this chapter if the individual rendering such service has not previously rendered service, other than as such a delegate, which may be included in his “years of service” for purposes of the Railroad Retirement Act. Nothing in the regulations prescribed for purposes of chapter 24 (relating to wage withholding) which provides an exclusion from “wages” as used in such chapter shall be construed to require a similar exclusion from “compensation” in regulations prescribed for purposes of this chapter.</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I79" class="indent3 firstIndent-2" id="id45741692-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2">
          <ns0:num value="2" class="bold">(2)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:heading class="bold"> Application of contribution bases</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I18" class="indent4 firstIndent-2" id="id45741693-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/A">
            <ns0:num value="A" class="bold">(A)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:heading class="bold"> Compensation in excess of applicable base excluded</ns0:heading>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I77" class="indent5 firstIndent-2" id="id45741694-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/A/i">
              <ns0:num value="i" class="bold">(i)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:heading class="bold"> In general</ns0:heading>
              <ns0:content>
                <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3">The term “compensation” does not include that part of remuneration paid during any calendar year to an individual by an employer after remuneration equal to the applicable base has been paid during such calendar year to such individual by such employer for services rendered as an employee to such employer.</ns0:p>
              </ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I77" class="indent5 firstIndent-2" id="id45741695-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/A/ii">
              <ns0:num value="ii" class="bold">(ii)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:heading class="bold"> Remuneration not treated as compensation excluded</ns0:heading>
              <ns0:content>
                <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3">There shall not be taken into account under clause (i) remuneration which (without regard to clause (i)) is not treated as compensation under this subsection.</ns0:p>
              </ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I77" class="indent5 firstIndent-2" id="id45741696-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/A/iii">
              <ns0:num value="iii" class="bold">(iii)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:heading class="bold"> Hospital insurance taxes</ns0:heading>
              <ns0:chapeau style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3">Clause (i) shall not apply to—</ns0:chapeau>
              <ns0:subclause style="-uslm-lc:I16" class="indent4" id="id45741697-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/A/iii/I">
                <ns0:num value="I">(I)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> so much of the rate applicable under section 3201(a) or 3221(a) as does not exceed the rate of tax in effect under section 3101(b), and</ns0:content>
              </ns0:subclause>
              <ns0:subclause style="-uslm-lc:I16" class="indent4" id="id45741698-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/A/iii/II">
                <ns0:num value="II">(II)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> so much of the rate applicable under section 3211(a) as does not exceed the rate of tax in effect under section 1401(b).</ns0:content>
              </ns0:subclause>
            </ns0:clause>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I18" class="indent4 firstIndent-2" id="id45741699-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/B">
            <ns0:num value="B" class="bold">(B)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:heading class="bold"> Applicable base</ns0:heading>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I77" class="indent5 firstIndent-2" id="id4574169a-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/B/i">
              <ns0:num value="i" class="bold">(i)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:heading class="bold"> Tier 1 taxes</ns0:heading>
              <ns0:content>
                <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3">Except as provided in clause (ii), the term “applicable base” means for any calendar year the contribution and benefit base determined under section 230 of the Social Security Act for such calendar year.</ns0:p>
              </ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I77" class="indent5 firstIndent-2" id="id4574169b-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/B/ii">
              <ns0:num value="ii" class="bold">(ii)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:heading class="bold"> Tier 2 taxes, etc.</ns0:heading>
              <ns0:chapeau style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3">For purposes of—</ns0:chapeau>
              <ns0:subclause style="-uslm-lc:I16" class="indent4" id="id4574169c-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/B/ii/I">
                <ns0:num value="I">(I)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> the taxes imposed by sections 3201(b), 3211(b), and 3221(b), and</ns0:content>
              </ns0:subclause>
              <ns0:subclause style="-uslm-lc:I16" class="indent4" id="id4574169d-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/B/ii/II">
                <ns0:num value="II">(II)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> computing average monthly compensation under section 3(j) of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1974 (except with respect to annuity amounts determined under subsection (a) or (f)(3) of section 3 of such Act),</ns0:content>
              </ns0:subclause>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:continuation style="-uslm-lc:I66" class="indent3 firstIndent-1"> clause (2) of the first sentence, and the second sentence, of subsection (c) of section 230 of the Social Security Act shall be disregarded.</ns0:continuation>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I18" class="indent4 firstIndent-2" id="id4574169e-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/C">
            <ns0:num value="C" class="bold">(C)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:heading class="bold"> Successor employers</ns0:heading>
            <ns0:chapeau style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2">For purposes of this paragraph, the second sentence of section 3121(a)(1) (relating to successor employers) shall apply, except that—</ns0:chapeau>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3" id="id4574169f-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/C/i">
              <ns0:num value="i">(i)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:content> the term “services” shall be substituted for “employment” each place it appears,</ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3" id="id457416a0-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/C/ii">
              <ns0:num value="ii">(ii)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:content> the term “compensation” shall be substituted for “remuneration (other than remuneration referred to in the succeeding paragraphs of this subsection)” each place it appears, and</ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3" id="id457416a1-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/2/C/iii">
              <ns0:num value="iii">(iii)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:content> the terms “employer”, “services”, and “compensation” shall have the meanings given such terms by this section.</ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416a2-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/3">
          <ns0:num value="3">(3)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> Solely for purposes of the taxes imposed by section 3201 and other provisions of this chapter insofar as they relate to such taxes, the term “compensation” also includes cash tips received by an employee in any calendar month in the course of his employment by an employer unless the amount of such cash tips is less than $20.</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416a3-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4">
          <ns0:num value="4">(4)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416a4-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4/A">
            <ns0:num value="A">(A)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:chapeau> For purposes of applying sections 3201(a), 3211(a), and 3221(a), in the case of payments made to an employee or any of his dependents on account of sickness or accident disability, clause (i) of the second sentence of paragraph (1) shall exclude from the term “compensation” only—</ns0:chapeau>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="id457416a5-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4/A/i">
              <ns0:num value="i">(i)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:content> payments which are received under a workmen’s compensation law, and</ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
            <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="id457416a6-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4/A/ii">
              <ns0:num value="ii">(ii)</ns0:num>
              <ns0:content> benefits received under the Railroad Retirement Act of 1974.</ns0:content>
            </ns0:clause>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416a7-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4/B">
            <ns0:num value="B">(B)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:content> Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for purposes of the sections specified in subparagraph (A), the term “compensation” shall include benefits paid under section 2(a) of the Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act for days of sickness, except to the extent that such sickness (as determined in accordance with standards prescribed by the Railroad Retirement Board) is the result of on-the-job injury.</ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416a8-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4/C">
            <ns0:num value="C">(C)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:content> Under regulations prescribed by the Secretary, subparagraphs (A) and (B) shall not apply to payments made after the expiration of a 6-month period comparable to the 6-month period described in section 3121(a)(4).</ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416a9-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/4/D">
            <ns0:num value="D">(D)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:content> Except as otherwise provided in regulations prescribed by the Secretary, any third party which makes a payment included in compensation solely by reason of subparagraph (A) or (B) shall be treated for purposes of this chapter as the employer with respect to such compensation.</ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416aa-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/5">
          <ns0:num value="5">(5)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> The term “compensation” shall not include any benefit provided to or on behalf of an employee if at the time such benefit is provided it is reasonable to believe that the employee will be able to exclude such benefit from income under section 74(c), 108(f)(4), 117, or 132.</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="id457416ab-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/6">
          <ns0:num value="6">(6)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> The term “compensation” shall not include any payment made, or benefit furnished, to or for the benefit of an employee if at the time of such payment or such furnishing it is reasonable to believe that the employee will be able to exclude such payment or benefit from income under section 127.</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" status="repealed" id="id457416ac-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/7">
          <ns0:num value="7">[(7)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:content> Repealed. <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/113/295/dA/tII/s221/a/19/B/v">Pub. L. 113–295, div. A, title II, § 221(a)(19)(B)(v)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="2014-12-19">Dec. 19, 2014</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/128/4040">128 Stat. 4040</ns0:ref>.]</ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I79" class="indent3 firstIndent-2" id="id457416ad-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/8">
          <ns0:num value="8" class="bold">(8)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:heading class="bold"> Treatment of certain deferred compensation and salary reduction arrangements</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I18" class="indent4 firstIndent-2" id="id457416ae-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/8/A">
            <ns0:num value="A" class="bold">(A)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:heading class="bold"> Certain employer contributions treated as compensation</ns0:heading>
            <ns0:content>
              <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2">Nothing in any paragraph of this subsection (other than paragraph (2)) shall exclude from the term “compensation” any amount described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of section 3121(v)(1).</ns0:p>
            </ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I18" class="indent4 firstIndent-2" id="id457416af-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/8/B">
            <ns0:num value="B" class="bold">(B)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:heading class="bold"> Treatment of certain nonqualified deferred compensation</ns0:heading>
            <ns0:content>
              <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2">The rules of section 3121(v)(2) which apply for purposes of chapter 21 shall also apply for purposes of this chapter.</ns0:p>
            </ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I79" class="indent3 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b0-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/9">
          <ns0:num value="9" class="bold">(9)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:heading class="bold"> Meals and lodging</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:content>
            <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1">The term “compensation” shall not include the value of meals or lodging furnished by or on behalf of the employer if at the time of such furnishing it is reasonable to believe that the employee will be able to exclude such items from income under section 119.</ns0:p>
          </ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I79" class="indent3 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b1-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/10">
          <ns0:num value="10" class="bold">(10)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:heading class="bold"> Archer MSA contributions</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:content>
            <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1">The term “compensation” shall not include any payment made to or for the benefit of an employee if at the time of such payment it is reasonable to believe that the employee will be able to exclude such payment from income under section 106(b).</ns0:p>
          </ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I79" class="indent3 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b2-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/11">
          <ns0:num value="11" class="bold">(11)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:heading class="bold"> Health savings account contributions</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:content>
            <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1">The term “compensation” shall not include any payment made to or for the benefit of an employee if at the time of such payment it is reasonable to believe that the employee will be able to exclude such payment from income under section 106(d).</ns0:p>
          </ns0:content>
        </ns0:paragraph>
        <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I79" class="indent3 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b3-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/12">
          <ns0:num value="12" class="bold">(12)</ns0:num>
          <ns0:heading class="bold"> Qualified stock options</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:chapeau style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1">The term “compensation” shall not include any remuneration on account of—</ns0:chapeau>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="id457416b4-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/12/A">
            <ns0:num value="A">(A)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:content> a transfer of a share of stock to any individual pursuant to an exercise of an incentive stock option (as defined in section 422(b)) or under an employee stock purchase plan (as defined in section 423(b)), or</ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
          <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="id457416b5-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/e/12/B">
            <ns0:num value="B">(B)</ns0:num>
            <ns0:content> any disposition by the individual of such stock.</ns0:content>
          </ns0:subparagraph>
        </ns0:paragraph>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b6-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/f">
        <ns0:num value="f" class="bold">(f)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Company</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, the term “company” includes corporations, associations, and joint-stock companies.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b7-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/g">
        <ns0:num value="g" class="bold">(g)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Carrier</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, the term “carrier” means a rail carrier subject to part A of subtitle IV of title 49.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b8-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/h">
        <ns0:num value="h" class="bold">(h)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Tips constituting compensation, time deemed paid</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, tips which constitute compensation for purposes of the taxes imposed by section 3201 shall be deemed to be paid at the time a written statement including such tips is furnished to the employer pursuant to section 6053(a) or (if no statement including such tips is so furnished) at the time received.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:subsection style="-uslm-lc:I19" class="indent2 firstIndent-2" id="id457416b9-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a" identifier="/us/usc/t26/s3231/i">
        <ns0:num value="i" class="bold">(i)</ns0:num>
        <ns0:heading class="bold"> Concurrent employment by 2 or more employers</ns0:heading>
        <ns0:content>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, if 2 or more related corporations which are employers concurrently employ the same individual and compensate such individual through a common paymaster which is 1 of such corporations, each such corporation shall be considered to have paid as remuneration to such individual only the amounts actually disbursed by it to such individual and shall not be considered to have paid as remuneration to such individual amounts actually disbursed to such individual by another of such corporations.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:content>
      </ns0:subsection>
      <ns0:sourceCredit id="id457416ba-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">(<ns0:ref href="/us/act/1954-08-16/ch736">Aug. 16, 1954, ch. 736</ns0:ref>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/68A/434">68A Stat. 434</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/act/1954-08-31/ch1164">Aug. 31, 1954, ch. 1164</ns0:ref>, pt. II, § 206(b), <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/68/1040">68 Stat. 1040</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/89/212/s2/b">Pub. L. 89–212, § 2(b)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1965-09-29">Sept. 29, 1965</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/79/859">79 Stat. 859</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/90/624/s1">Pub. L. 90–624, § 1</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1968-10-22">Oct. 22, 1968</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/82/1316">82 Stat. 1316</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/92/tII/s203/b">Pub. L. 94–92, title II, § 203(b)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/89/465">89 Stat. 465</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93/tII">Pub. L. 94–93, title II</ns0:ref>, §§ 204–206, <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/89/466">89 Stat. 466</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/455/tXIX">Pub. L. 94–455, title XIX</ns0:ref>, §§ 1903(a)(10), 1906(b)(13)(A), <ns0:date date="1976-10-04">Oct. 4, 1976</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/90/1808">90 Stat. 1808</ns0:ref>, 1834; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/547/s4/b">Pub. L. 94–547, § 4(b)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1976-10-18">Oct. 18, 1976</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/90/2526">90 Stat. 2526</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/95/473/s2/a/2/G">Pub. L. 95–473, § 2(a)(2)(G)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1978-10-17">Oct. 17, 1978</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/92/1465">92 Stat. 1465</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/tVII">Pub. L. 97–34, title VII</ns0:ref>, §§ 741(d)(2), 743(a)–(c), <ns0:date date="1981-08-13">Aug. 13, 1981</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/95/347">95 Stat. 347</ns0:ref>, 348; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/123/s3/c">Pub. L. 97–123, § 3(c)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1981-12-29">Dec. 29, 1981</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/95/1662">95 Stat. 1662</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/tII/s225/a/1">Pub. L. 98–76, title II, § 225(a)(1)</ns0:ref>, (3), (b), (c)(1)(C), (6)–(8), <ns0:date date="1983-08-12">Aug. 12, 1983</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/97/424">97 Stat. 424</ns0:ref>, 425; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/369/dA/tV/s531/d/2">Pub. L. 98–369, div. A, title V, § 531(d)(2)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1984-07-18">July 18, 1984</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/98/884">98 Stat. 884</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/611/s1/f">Pub. L. 98–611, § 1(f)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1984-10-31">Oct. 31, 1984</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/98/3178">98 Stat. 3178</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/612/s1/c">Pub. L. 98–612, § 1(c)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1984-10-31">Oct. 31, 1984</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/98/3181">98 Stat. 3181</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/tI/s122/e/2">Pub. L. 99–514, title I, § 122(e)(2)</ns0:ref>, title XVIII, § 1899A(41), <ns0:date date="1986-10-22">Oct. 22, 1986</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/100/2112">100 Stat. 2112</ns0:ref>, 2960; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/tI">Pub. L. 100–647, title I</ns0:ref>, §§ 1001(d)(2)(C)(ii), 1011B(a)(22)(B), <ns0:date date="1988-11-10">Nov. 10, 1988</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/102/3351">102 Stat. 3351</ns0:ref>, 3486; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/140/tII/s203/a/2">Pub. L. 101–140, title II, § 203(a)(2)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1989-11-08">Nov. 8, 1989</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/103/830">103 Stat. 830</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/tX">Pub. L. 101–239, title X</ns0:ref>, §§ 10205(a), 10206(a), (b), 10207(a), (b), <ns0:date date="1989-12-19">Dec. 19, 1989</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/103/2474-2476">103 Stat. 2474–2476</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/508/tXI">Pub. L. 101–508, title XI</ns0:ref>, §§ 11331(c), 11704(a)(19), <ns0:date date="1990-11-05">Nov. 5, 1990</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/104/1388-468">104 Stat. 1388–468</ns0:ref>, 1388–519; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/66/tXIII/s13207/c">Pub. L. 103–66, title XIII, § 13207(c)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1993-08-10">Aug. 10, 1993</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/107/468">107 Stat. 468</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/296/tIII/s320/a/1/D">Pub. L. 103–296, title III, § 320(a)(1)(D)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1994-08-15">Aug. 15, 1994</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/108/1535">108 Stat. 1535</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/88/tIII/s304/d">Pub. L. 104–88, title III, § 304(d)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1995-12-29">Dec. 29, 1995</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/109/944">109 Stat. 944</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/191/tIII/s301/c/2/A">Pub. L. 104–191, title III, § 301(c)(2)(A)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1996-08-21">Aug. 21, 1996</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/110/2049">110 Stat. 2049</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/106/554/s1/a/7/tII/s202/b/5">Pub. L. 106–554, § 1(a)(7) [title II, § 202(b)(5)]</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="2000-12-21">Dec. 21, 2000</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/114/2763">114 Stat. 2763</ns0:ref>, 2763A–629; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/107/90/tII/s204/e/3">Pub. L. 107–90, title II, § 204(e)(3)</ns0:ref>, (4), <ns0:date date="2001-12-21">Dec. 21, 2001</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/115/893">115 Stat. 893</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/173/tXII/s1201/d/2/A">Pub. L. 108–173, title XII, § 1201(d)(2)(A)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="2003-12-08">Dec. 8, 2003</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/117/2477">117 Stat. 2477</ns0:ref>; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/tII/s251/a/2">Pub. L. 108–357, title II, § 251(a)(2)</ns0:ref>, title III, § 320(b)(2), <ns0:date date="2004-10-22">Oct. 22, 2004</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/118/1458">118 Stat. 1458</ns0:ref>, 1473; <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/113/295/dA/tII/s221/a/19/B/v">Pub. L. 113–295, div. A, title II, § 221(a)(19)(B)(v)</ns0:ref>, (100)(D), <ns0:date date="2014-12-19">Dec. 19, 2014</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/128/4040">128 Stat. 4040</ns0:ref>, 4052.)</ns0:sourceCredit>
      <ns0:notes type="uscNote" id="id457416bb-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" role="crossHeading" topic="editorialNotes" id="id457416bc-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered">
            <ns0:b>Editorial Notes</ns0:b>
          </ns0:heading>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I75" topic="referencesInText" id="id457416bd-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">References in Text</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">The Railway Labor Act, referred to in subsecs. (a) and (c), is <ns0:ref href="/us/act/1926-05-20/ch347">act May 20, 1926, ch. 347</ns0:ref>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/44/577">44 Stat. 577</ns0:ref>, which is classified principally to chapter 8 (§ 151 et seq.) of Title 45, Railroads. For complete classification of this Act to the Code, see <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s151">section 151 of Title 45</ns0:ref> and Tables.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Section 1 of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1937, referred to in subsec. (d)(7), was classified to <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s228a">section 228a of Title 45</ns0:ref>, Railroads, prior to being omitted from the Code. The subject matter of section 228a is covered by <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s231">section 231 of Title 45</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Section 230 of the Social Security Act, referred to in subsec. (e)(2)(B), is classified to <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t42/s430">section 430 of Title 42</ns0:ref>, The Public Health and Welfare.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Section 3(a), (f)(3), (j) of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1974, referred to in subsec. (e)(2)(B)(ii)(II), is classified to section 231b(a), (f)(3), (j) of Title 45, Railroads.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">The Railroad Retirement Act of 1974, referred to in subsec. (e)(4)(A)(ii), is <ns0:ref href="/us/act/1935-08-29/ch812">act Aug. 29, 1935, ch. 812</ns0:ref>, as amended generally by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/93/445/tI/s101">Pub. L. 93–445, title I, § 101</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1974-10-16">Oct. 16, 1974</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/88/1305">88 Stat. 1305</ns0:ref>, which is classified generally to subchapter IV (§ 231 et seq.) of chapter 9 of Title 45, Railroads. For further details and complete classification of this Act to the Code, see Codification note set out preceding <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s231">section 231 of Title 45</ns0:ref>, <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s231t">section 231t of Title 45</ns0:ref>, and Tables.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Section 101(a)(15) of the Immigration and Nationality Act, referred to in subsec. (e)(1), is classified to <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t8/s1101/a/15">section 1101(a)(15) of Title 8</ns0:ref>, Aliens and Nationality.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Section 2(a) of the Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act, referred to in subsec. (e)(4)(B), is classified to <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s352/a">section 352(a) of Title 45</ns0:ref>, Railroads.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="amendments" id="id457416be-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Amendments</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">2014—Subsec. (b). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/113/295/s221/a/100/D">Pub. L. 113–295, § 221(a)(100)(D)</ns0:ref>, in first sentence substituted “compensation.” for “compensation; except that the term ‘employee’ shall include an employee of a local lodge or division defined as an employer in subsection (a) only if he was in the service of or in the employment relation to a carrier on or after <ns0:date date="1935-08-29">August 29, 1935</ns0:date>.” and struck out second sentence, which included pars. (1) to (4) and concluding provisions relating to an individual deemed to have been in the employment relation to a carrier on <ns0:date date="1935-08-29">Aug. 29, 1935</ns0:date>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(7). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/113/295/s221/a/19/B/v">Pub. L. 113–295, § 221(a)(19)(B)(v)</ns0:ref>, struck out par. (7) which read as follows: “The term ‘compensation’ shall not include any contribution, payment, or service provided by an employer which may be excluded from the gross income of an employee, his spouse, or his dependents, under the provisions of section 120 (relating to amounts received under qualified group legal services plans).”</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">2004—Subsec. (e)(5). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/s320/b/2">Pub. L. 108–357, § 320(b)(2)</ns0:ref>, inserted “108(f)(4),” after “74(c),”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(12). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/s251/a/2">Pub. L. 108–357, § 251(a)(2)</ns0:ref>, added par. (12).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">2003—Subsec. (e)(11). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/173">Pub. L. 108–173</ns0:ref> added par. (11).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">2001—Subsec. (e)(2)(A)(iii)(II). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/107/90/s204/e/3">Pub. L. 107–90, § 204(e)(3)</ns0:ref>, substituted “3211(a)” for “3211(a)(1)”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(2)(B)(ii)(I). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/107/90/s204/e/4">Pub. L. 107–90, § 204(e)(4)</ns0:ref>, substituted “3211(b)” for “3211(a)(2)”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(4)(A). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/107/90/s204/e/3">Pub. L. 107–90, § 204(e)(3)</ns0:ref>, substituted “3211(a)” for “3211(a)(1)”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">2000—Subsec. (e)(10). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/106/554">Pub. L. 106–554</ns0:ref> substituted “Archer MSA” for “Medical savings account” in heading.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1996—Subsec. (e)(10). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/191">Pub. L. 104–191</ns0:ref> added par. (10).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1995—Subsec. (a). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/88/s304/d/1">Pub. L. 104–88, § 304(d)(1)</ns0:ref>, substituted “Surface Transportation Board” for “Interstate Commerce Commission”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (g). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/88/s304/d/2">Pub. L. 104–88, § 304(d)(2)</ns0:ref>, substituted “a rail carrier subject to part A of subtitle IV” for “an express carrier, sleeping car carrier, or rail carrier providing transportation subject to subchapter I of chapter 105”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1994—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/296">Pub. L. 103–296</ns0:ref> substituted “(J), (M), or (Q)” for “(J), or (M)” in two places.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1993—Subsec. (e)(2)(A)(iii). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/66/s13207/c/1">Pub. L. 103–66, § 13207(c)(1)</ns0:ref>, added cl. (iii).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(2)(B)(i). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/66/s13207/c/2">Pub. L. 103–66, § 13207(c)(2)</ns0:ref>, amended heading and text of cl. (i) generally. Prior to amendment, text read as follows:</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">“(I) <ns0:inline class="small-caps">In general</ns0:inline>.—Except as provided in subclause (II) of this clause and in clause (ii), the term ‘applicable base’ means for any calendar year the contribution and benefit base determined under section 230 of the Social Security Act for such calendar year.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">“(II) <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Hospital insurance taxes</ns0:inline>.—For purposes of applying so much of the rate applicable under section 3201(a) or 3221(a) (as the case may be) as does not exceed the rate of tax in effect under section 3101(b), and for purposes of applying so much of the rate of tax applicable under section 3211(a)(1) as does not exceed the rate of tax in effect under section 1401(b), the term ‘applicable base’ means for any calendar year the applicable contribution base determined under section 3121(x)(2) for such calendar year.”</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1990—Subsec. (e)(2)(B)(i). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/508/s11331/c">Pub. L. 101–508, § 11331(c)</ns0:ref>, amended cl. (i) generally. Prior to amendment, cl. (i) read as follows: “Except as provided in clause (ii), the term ‘applicable base’ means for any calendar year the contribution and benefit base determined under section 230 of the Social Security Act for such calendar year.”</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(8) to (10). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/508/s11704/a/19">Pub. L. 101–508, § 11704(a)(19)</ns0:ref>, redesignated pars. (9) and (10) as (8) and (9), respectively.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1989—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/s10207/b">Pub. L. 101–239, § 10207(b)</ns0:ref>, inserted at end “Nothing in the regulations prescribed for purposes of chapter 24 (relating to wage withholding) which provides an exclusion from ‘wages’ as used in such chapter shall be construed to require a similar exclusion from ‘compensation’ in regulations prescribed for purposes of this chapter.”</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/s10206/a">Pub. L. 101–239, § 10206(a)</ns0:ref>, substituted “(iii)” for “or (iii)” and inserted “, or (iv) any remuneration which would not (if chapter 21 applied to such remuneration) be treated as wages (as defined in section 3121(a)) by reason of section 3121(a)(5)”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/s10205/a">Pub. L. 101–239, § 10205(a)</ns0:ref>, inserted “or death, except that this clause does not apply to a payment for group-term life insurance to the extent that such payment is includible in the gross income of the employee” before “, (ii) tips”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(8). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/140">Pub. L. 101–140</ns0:ref> amended subsec. (e) to read as if amendments by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1011B/a/22/B">Pub. L. 100–647, § 1011B(a)(22)(B)</ns0:ref>, had not been enacted, see 1988 Amendment note below.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(9). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/s10206/b">Pub. L. 101–239, § 10206(b)</ns0:ref>, added par. (9).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(10). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/s10207/a">Pub. L. 101–239, § 10207(a)</ns0:ref>, added par. (10).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1988—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1001/d/2/C/ii">Pub. L. 100–647, § 1001(d)(2)(C)(ii)</ns0:ref>, substituted “(F), (J), or (M)” for “(F) or (J)” in two places.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(8). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1011B/a/22/B">Pub. L. 100–647, § 1011B(a)(22)(B)</ns0:ref>, added par. (8).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1986—Subsec. (e)(5). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/s122/e/2">Pub. L. 99–514, § 122(e)(2)</ns0:ref>, inserted reference to section 74(c).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(6), (7). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/s1899A/41">Pub. L. 99–514, § 1899A(41)</ns0:ref>, redesignated par. (6), relating to amounts excludable under section 120, as (7).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1984—Subsec. (e)(5). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/369/s531/d/2">Pub. L. 98–369, § 531(d)(2)</ns0:ref>, added par. (5).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(6). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/611">Pub. L. 98–611</ns0:ref> added par. (6) relating to amounts excludable under section 127.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/612">Pub. L. 98–612</ns0:ref> added par. (6) relating to amounts excludable under section 120.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1983—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s225/a/3">Pub. L. 98–76, § 225(a)(3)</ns0:ref>, struck out provisions that compensation which was paid in one calendar month but which would be payable in a prior or subsequent taxable month but for the fact prescribed date of payment would fall on a Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday would be deemed to have been paid in such prior or subsequent taxable month and that compensation which was earned during the period for which the Secretary would require a return of taxes under this chapter to be made and which was payable during the calendar month following such period would be deemed to have been paid during such period only.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(2). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s225/a/1">Pub. L. 98–76, § 225(a)(1)</ns0:ref>, amended par. (2) generally, substituting provisions which exclude compensation in excess of applicable base, which define “applicable base”, and which provide for the applicability of successor employer provisions to this paragraph, for provisions that a payment made by an employer to an individual through the employer’s payroll would be presumed, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, to be compensation for service rendered by such individual as an employee of the employer in the period with respect to which the payment was made, that an employee receiving retroactive wage payments would be deemed to be paid compensation in the period during which such compensation was earned only upon a written request by such employee, made within six months following the payment, and a showing that such compensation was earned during a period other than the period in which it was paid, that an employee would be deemed to be paid “for time lost” the amount he was paid by an employer with respect to an identifiable period of absence from the active service of the employer, including absence on account of personal injury, and the amount he was paid by the employer for loss of earnings resulting from his displacement to a less remunerative position or occupation, and that if a payment was made by an employer with respect to a personal injury and included pay for time lost, the total payment would be deemed to be paid for time lost unless, at the time of payment, a part of such payment was specifically apportioned to factors other than time lost, in which event only such part of the payment as was not so apportioned would be deemed to be paid for time lost.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(3). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s225/c/1/C">Pub. L. 98–76, § 225(c)(1)(C)</ns0:ref>, (6), substituted “taxes imposed by section 3201” for “tax imposed by section 3201”, and “such taxes” for “such tax”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(4)(A). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s225/c/7">Pub. L. 98–76, § 225(c)(7)</ns0:ref>, substituted “3201(a), 3211(a)(1), and 3221(a)” for “3201(b) and 3221(b) (and so much of section 3211(a) as relates to the rates of the taxes imposed by sections 3101 and 3111)”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (h). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s225/c/8">Pub. L. 98–76, § 225(c)(8)</ns0:ref>, substituted “taxes imposed by section 3201” for “tax imposed under section 3201”, and struck out “; and tips so deemed to be paid in any month shall be deemed paid for services rendered in such month” after “time received”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (i). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s225/b">Pub. L. 98–76, § 225(b)</ns0:ref>, added subsec. (i).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1981—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/s743/a">Pub. L. 97–34, § 743(a)</ns0:ref>, inserted after third sentence provision that “Compensation which is paid in one calendar month but which would be payable in a prior or subsequent taxable month but for the fact that prescribed date of payment would fall on a Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday shall be deemed to have been paid in such prior or subsequent taxable month.”</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/s741/d/2">Pub. L. 97–34, § 741(d)(2)</ns0:ref>, struck out cl. (iii) exclusion from term “compensation” the voluntary payment by an employer, without deduction from the remuneration of the employee, of the tax imposed on such employee by section 3201, redesignated as cl. (iii) provisions formerly designated (iv).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(2). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/s743/b">Pub. L. 97–34, § 743(b)</ns0:ref>, (c), inserted first sentence respecting presumption of a payment through the employer’s payroll as being compensation for services rendered as an employee in the period with respect to which payment is made, and in second sentence following “an employee” inserted “receiving retroactive wage payments”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(4). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/123">Pub. L. 97–123</ns0:ref> added par. (4).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1978—Subsec. (g). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/95/473">Pub. L. 95–473</ns0:ref> substituted “express carrier, sleeping car carrier, or rail carrier providing transportation subject to subchapter I of chapter 105 of title 49” for “express company, sleeping-car company, or carrier by railroad, subject to part I of the Interstate Commerce Act (49 U.S.C., chapter 1)”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1976—Subsec. (a). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/455">Pub. L. 94–455</ns0:ref>, §§ 1903(a)(10)(A), 1906(b)(13)(A), struck out “<ns0:ref href="/us/stat/44/577">44 Stat. 577</ns0:ref>;” before “45 U.S.C., chapter 8” and “or his delegate” after “Secretary”, respectively.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (b). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/455/s1903/a/10/B">Pub. L. 94–455, § 1903(a)(10)(B)</ns0:ref>, struck out in provisions following par. (4) “<ns0:ref href="/us/stat/50/312">50 Stat. 312</ns0:ref>;” before “<ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s228f">45 U.S.C. 228f</ns0:ref>”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (c). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/455/s1903/a/10/C">Pub. L. 94–455, § 1903(a)(10)(C)</ns0:ref>, struck out “<ns0:ref href="/us/stat/44/577">44 Stat. 577</ns0:ref>;” before “45 U.S.C. chapter 8”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (d)(7). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/455/s1903/a/10/D">Pub. L. 94–455, § 1903(a)(10)(D)</ns0:ref>, struck out “<ns0:ref href="/us/stat/50/308">50 Stat. 308</ns0:ref>;” before “<ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s228a">45 U.S.C. 228a</ns0:ref>”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/547">Pub. L. 94–547</ns0:ref> provided that “compensation” not include amount of any payment (including any amount paid by an employer for insurance or annuities, or into a fund, to provide for any such payment) made to, or on behalf of, an employee or any of his dependents under a plan or system established by an employer which makes provision for his employees generally (or for his employees generally and their dependents) or for a class or classes of his employees (or for a class or classes of his employees and their dependents), on account of sickness or accident disability or medical or hospitalization expenses in connection with sickness or accident disability, or an amount paid specifically—either as an advance, as reimbursement or allowance—for traveling or other bona fide and necessary expenses incurred or reasonably expected to be incurred in the business of the employer provided any such payment is identified by the employer either by a separate payment or by specifically indicating the separate amounts where both wages and expense reimbursement or allowance are combined in a single payment.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/455/s1906/b/13/A">Pub. L. 94–455, § 1906(b)(13)(A)</ns0:ref>, struck out “or his delegate” after “Secretary”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1975—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93/s204">Pub. L. 94–93, § 204</ns0:ref>, substituted “paid to an individual for services rendered as an employee to one or more employers” for “earned by an individual for services rendered as an employee to one or more employers, or as an employee representative, including remuneration paid for time lost as an employee, but remuneration paid for time lost shall be deemed earned in the month in which such time is lost”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/92">Pub. L. 94–92</ns0:ref> increased from $3 to $25 amount of compensation earned in the service of a local lodge or division of a railway-labor-organization employer to be disregarded with respect to any calendar month in the determination of amount of taxes under sections 3201 and 3221.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(2). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93">Pub. L. 94–93</ns0:ref>, §§ 205, 206, substituted provision that an employee shall be deemed to be paid compensation in the period during which such compensation is earned only upon a written request by such employee, made within six months following the payment, and a showing that such compensation was earned during a period other than the period in which it was paid for provision that a payment made by an employer to an individual through the employer’s payroll shall be presumed, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, to be compensation for service rendered by such individual as an employee of the employer in the period with respect to which payment is made.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1968—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/90/624">Pub. L. 90–624</ns0:ref> inserted provision excluding remuneration for service performed by nonresident alien individuals temporarily in the United States as participants in a cultural exchange or training program.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1965—Subsec. (e)(1). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/89/212/s2/b/1">Pub. L. 89–212, § 2(b)(1)</ns0:ref>, inserted “(except as is provided under paragraph (3))”.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (e)(3). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/89/212/s2/b/2">Pub. L. 89–212, § 2(b)(2)</ns0:ref>, added par. (3).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Subsec. (h). <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/89/212/s2/b/3">Pub. L. 89–212, § 2(b)(3)</ns0:ref>, added subsec. (h).</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">1954—Subsec. (e)(1). Act <ns0:date date="1954-08-31">Aug. 31, 1954</ns0:date>, excluded from taxation compensation, for service as a delegate to a national or international convention of a railway labor organization, of any person who has no other previous creditable service.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" role="crossHeading" topic="statutoryNotes" id="id457687bf-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered">
            <ns0:b>Statutory Notes and Related Subsidiaries</ns0:b>
          </ns0:heading>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c0-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 2014 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/113/295">Pub. L. 113–295</ns0:ref> effective <ns0:date date="2014-12-19">Dec. 19, 2014</ns0:date>, subject to a savings provision, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/113/295/s221/b">section 221(b) of Pub. L. 113–295</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s1">section 1 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c1-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 2004 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/s251/a/2">section 251(a)(2) of Pub. L. 108–357</ns0:ref> applicable to stock acquired pursuant to options exercised after <ns0:date date="2004-10-22">Oct. 22, 2004</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/s251/d">section 251(d) of Pub. L. 108–357</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s421">section 421 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/s320/b/2">section 320(b)(2) of Pub. L. 108–357</ns0:ref> applicable to amounts received by an individual in taxable years beginning after <ns0:date date="2003-12-31">Dec. 31, 2003</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/357/s320/c">section 320(c) of Pub. L. 108–357</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s108">section 108 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c2-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 2003 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/173">Pub. L. 108–173</ns0:ref> applicable to taxable years beginning after <ns0:date date="2003-12-31">Dec. 31, 2003</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/108/173/s1201/k">section 1201(k) of Pub. L. 108–173</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s62">section 62 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c3-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 2001 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/107/90">Pub. L. 107–90</ns0:ref> applicable to calendar years beginning after <ns0:date date="2001-12-31">Dec. 31, 2001</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/107/90/s204/f">section 204(f) of Pub. L. 107–90</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s24">section 24 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c4-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1996 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/191">Pub. L. 104–191</ns0:ref> applicable to taxable years beginning after <ns0:date date="1996-12-31">Dec. 31, 1996</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/191/s301/j">section 301(j) of Pub. L. 104–191</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s62">section 62 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c5-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1995 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/88">Pub. L. 104–88</ns0:ref> effective <ns0:date date="1996-01-01">Jan. 1, 1996</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/104/88/s2">section 2 of Pub. L. 104–88</ns0:ref>, set out as an Effective Date note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t49/s1301">section 1301 of Title 49</ns0:ref>, Transportation.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c6-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1994 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/296">Pub. L. 103–296</ns0:ref> effective with calendar quarter following <ns0:date date="1994-08-15">Aug. 15, 1994</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/296/s320/c">section 320(c) of Pub. L. 103–296</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s871">section 871 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c7-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1993 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/66">Pub. L. 103–66</ns0:ref> applicable to 1994 and later calendar years, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/103/66/s13207/e">section 13207(e) of Pub. L. 103–66</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s1402">section 1402 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c8-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1990 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/508/s11331/c">section 11331(c) of Pub. L. 101–508</ns0:ref> applicable to 1991 and later calendar years, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/508/s11331/e">section 11331(e) of Pub. L. 101–508</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s1402">section 1402 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687c9-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1989 Amendments</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/tX/s10205/b">Pub. L. 101–239, title X, § 10205(b)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1989-12-19">Dec. 19, 1989</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/103/2474">103 Stat. 2474</ns0:ref> provided that:<ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/101/239/tX/s10205/b">
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="1">“(1)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">In general</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:chapeau>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendment made by subsection (a) [amending this section] shall apply to—</ns0:chapeau>
                <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I22" class="indent1">
                  <ns0:num value="A">“(A)</ns0:num>
                  <ns0:content> group-term life insurance coverage in effect after <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>, and</ns0:content>
                </ns0:subparagraph>
                <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I22" class="indent1">
                  <ns0:num value="B">“(B)</ns0:num>
                  <ns0:content> remuneration paid before <ns0:date date="1990-01-01">January 1, 1990</ns0:date>, which the employer treated as compensation when paid.</ns0:content>
                </ns0:subparagraph>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="2">“(2)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Exception</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:content>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to payments by the employer (or a successor of such employer) for group-term life insurance for such employer’s former employees who separated from employment with the employer on or before <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>, to the extent that such payments are not for coverage for any such employee for any period for which such employee is employed by such employer (or a successor of such employer) after the date of such separation.</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="3">“(3)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Benefit determinations to take into account remuneration on which tax paid</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:content>The term ‘compensation’ as defined in section 1(h) of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1974 [<ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s231/h">45 U.S.C. 231(h)</ns0:ref>] includes any remuneration which is included in the term ‘compensation’ as defined in section 3231(e)(1) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 by reason of the amendment made by subsection (a).”</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
            </ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/tX/s10206/c">Pub. L. 101–239, title X, § 10206(c)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1989-12-19">Dec. 19, 1989</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/103/2475">103 Stat. 2475</ns0:ref>, provided that:<ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/101/239/tX/s10206/c">
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="1">“(1)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Subsection</ns0:inline> (a).—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:content>The amendment made by subsection (a) [amending this section] shall apply to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>.</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="2">“(2)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Subsection</ns0:inline> (b).—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:chapeau>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection—</ns0:chapeau>
                <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I22" class="indent1">
                  <ns0:num value="A">“(A)</ns0:num>
                  <ns0:heading>
                    <ns0:inline class="small-caps">In general</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:chapeau>The amendment made by subsection (b) [amending this section] shall apply to—</ns0:chapeau>
                  <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I23" class="indent2">
                    <ns0:num value="i">“(i)</ns0:num>
                    <ns0:content> remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>, and</ns0:content>
                  </ns0:clause>
                  <ns0:clause style="-uslm-lc:I23" class="indent2">
                    <ns0:num value="ii">“(ii)</ns0:num>
                    <ns0:content> remuneration paid before <ns0:date date="1990-01-01">January 1, 1990</ns0:date>, which the employer treated as compensation when paid.</ns0:content>
                  </ns0:clause>
                </ns0:subparagraph>
                <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I22" class="indent1">
                  <ns0:num value="B">“(B)</ns0:num>
                  <ns0:heading>
                    <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Benefit determinations to take into account remuneration on which tax paid</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:content>The term ‘compensation’ as defined in section 1(h) of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1974 [<ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s231/h">45 U.S.C. 231(h)</ns0:ref>] includes any remuneration which is included in the term ‘compensation’ as defined in section 3231(e)(1) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 by reason of the amendment made by subsection (b).</ns0:content>
                </ns0:subparagraph>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="3">“(3)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Special rule for certain payments</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:content>For purposes of applying the amendment made by subsection (b) to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>, which would have been taken into account before <ns0:date date="1990-01-01">January 1, 1990</ns0:date>, if such amendments had applied to periods before <ns0:date date="1990-01-01">January 1, 1990</ns0:date>, such remuneration shall be taken into account when paid (or, at the election of the payor, at the time which would be appropriate if such amendments had applied).</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="4">“(4)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Exception for certain 401</ns0:inline>(k) <ns0:inline class="small-caps">contributions</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:chapeau>The amendment made by subsection (b) shall not apply to employer contributions made during 1990 and attributable to services performed during 1989 under a qualified cash or deferred arrangement (as defined in section 401(k) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) if, under the terms of the arrangement as in effect on <ns0:date date="1989-06-15">June 15, 1989</ns0:date>—</ns0:chapeau>
                <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I22" class="indent1">
                  <ns0:num value="A">“(A)</ns0:num>
                  <ns0:content> the employee makes an election with respect to such contributions before <ns0:date date="1990-01-01">January 1, 1990</ns0:date>, and</ns0:content>
                </ns0:subparagraph>
                <ns0:subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I22" class="indent1">
                  <ns0:num value="B">“(B)</ns0:num>
                  <ns0:content> the employer identifies the amount of such contribution before <ns0:date date="1990-01-01">January 1, 1990</ns0:date>.</ns0:content>
                </ns0:subparagraph>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="5">“(5)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:heading>
                  <ns0:inline class="small-caps">Special rule with respect to nonqualified deferred compensation plans</ns0:inline>.—</ns0:heading>
                <ns0:content>In the case of an agreement in existence on <ns0:date date="1989-06-15">June 15, 1989</ns0:date>, between a nonqualified deferred compensation plan (as defined in section 3121(v)(2)(C) of such Code) and an individual, the amendment made by subsection (b) shall apply with respect to services performed by the individual after <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>. The preceding sentence shall not apply in the case of a plan to which section 457(a) of such Code applies.”</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
            </ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/tX/s10207/c">Pub. L. 101–239, title X, § 10207(c)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1989-12-19">Dec. 19, 1989</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/103/2476">103 Stat. 2476</ns0:ref>, provided that: <ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/101/239/tX/s10207/c">“The amendments made by this section [amending this section] shall apply to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1989-12-31">December 31, 1989</ns0:date>.”</ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/140">Pub. L. 101–140</ns0:ref> effective as if included in <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/s1151">section 1151 of Pub. L. 99–514</ns0:ref>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/140/s203/c">section 203(c) of Pub. L. 101–140</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s79">section 79 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687ca-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1988 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1001/d/2/C/ii">section 1001(d)(2)(C)(ii) of Pub. L. 100–647</ns0:ref> effective, except as otherwise provided, as if included in the provision of the Tax Reform Act of 1986, <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514">Pub. L. 99–514</ns0:ref>, to which such amendment relates, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1019/a">section 1019(a) of Pub. L. 100–647</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s1">section 1 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1011B/a/22/B">section 1011B(a)(22)(B) of Pub. L. 100–647</ns0:ref> not applicable to any individual who separated from service with the employer before <ns0:date date="1989-01-01">Jan. 1, 1989</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/647/s1011B/a/22/F">section 1011B(a)(22)(F) of Pub. L. 100–647</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3121">section 3121 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687cb-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1986 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/s122/e/2">section 122(e)(2) of Pub. L. 99–514</ns0:ref> applicable to prizes and awards granted after <ns0:date date="1986-12-31">Dec. 31, 1986</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/s151/c">section 151(c) of Pub. L. 99–514</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s1">section 1 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687cc-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1984 Amendments</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/612/s1/d/3">Pub. L. 98–612, § 1(d)(3)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1984-10-31">Oct. 31, 1984</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/98/3181">98 Stat. 3181</ns0:ref>, provided that: <ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/98/612/s1/d/3">“The amendment made by subsection (c) [amending this section] shall apply to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1984-12-31">December 31, 1984</ns0:date>.”</ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/611">Pub. L. 98–611</ns0:ref> applicable to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1984-12-31">Dec. 31, 1984</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/611/s1/g/3">section 1(g)(3) of Pub. L. 98–611</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s127">section 127 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/369">Pub. L. 98–369</ns0:ref> effective <ns0:date date="1985-01-01">Jan. 1, 1985</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/369/s531/h">section 531(h) of Pub. L. 98–369</ns0:ref>, set out as an Effective Date note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s132">section 132 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687cd-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1983 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76">Pub. L. 98–76</ns0:ref> applicable to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1984-12-31">Dec. 31, 1984</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/98/76/s227/a">section 227(a) of Pub. L. 98–76</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3201">section 3201 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687ce-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1981 Amendments</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/123">Pub. L. 97–123</ns0:ref> applicable to remuneration paid after <ns0:date date="1981-12-31">Dec. 31, 1981</ns0:date>, except as otherwise provided, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/123/s3/g">section 3(g) of Pub. L. 97–123</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3121">section 3121 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/s741/d/2">section 741(d)(2) of Pub. L. 97–34</ns0:ref> applicable to compensation paid for services rendered after <ns0:date date="1981-09-30">Sept. 30, 1981</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/s741/e">section 741(e) of Pub. L. 97–34</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3201">section 3201 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/34/tVII/s743/d">Pub. L. 97–34, title VII, § 743(d)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1981-08-13">Aug. 13, 1981</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/95/349">95 Stat. 349</ns0:ref>, provided that: <ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/97/34/tVII/s743/d">“The amendments made by this section [amending this section] shall apply for taxable years beginning after <ns0:date date="1981-12-31">December 31, 1981</ns0:date>.”</ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687cf-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1976 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/547/s4/c/2">Pub. L. 94–547, § 4(c)(2)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1976-10-18">Oct. 18, 1976</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/90/2527">90 Stat. 2527</ns0:ref>, provided that: <ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/94/547/s4/c/2">“The amendments made by subsection (b) of this section [amending this section] shall apply with respect to taxable years ending after <ns0:date date="1953-12-31">December 31, 1953</ns0:date>: <ns0:i>Provided, however</ns0:i>, That any taxes paid under the Railroad Retirement Tax Act [this chapter] prior to the date on which this Act is enacted [<ns0:date date="1976-10-18">Oct. 18, 1976</ns0:date>] shall not be affected or adjusted by reason of the amendments made by such subsection (b) except to the extent that the applicable period of limitation for the assessment of tax and the filing of a claim for credit or refund has not expired prior to the date on which this Act is enacted. If the applicable period of limitation for the filing of a claim for credit or refund would expire within the six-month period following the date on which this Act is enacted, the applicable period for the filing of such a claim for credit or refund shall be extended to include such six-month period.”</ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687d0-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1975 Amendments</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p>Amendment by sections 204 and 205 of <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93">Pub. L. 94–93</ns0:ref> applicable for taxable years ending on or after <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, and for taxable years ending before <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, as to which the period for assessment and collection of tax or the filing of a claim for credit or refund has not expired on <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, and amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93/s206">section 206 of Pub. L. 94–93</ns0:ref> applicable for taxable years beginning on or after <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>: <ns0:i>Provided, however</ns0:i>, That with respect to payment made prior to <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, the employee may file a written request under <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93/s206">section 206 of Pub. L. 94–93</ns0:ref> within six months after <ns0:date date="1975-08-09">Aug. 9, 1975</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/93/s207">section 207 of Pub. L. 94–93</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3201">section 3201 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/92">Pub. L. 94–92</ns0:ref> effective <ns0:date date="1975-01-01">Jan. 1, 1975</ns0:date>, and applicable only with respect to compensation paid for services rendered on or after <ns0:date date="1975-01-01">Jan. 1, 1975</ns0:date>, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/94/92/s203/c">section 203(c) of Pub. L. 94–92</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s1402">section 1402 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687d1-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1968 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p>
            <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/90/624/s4/a">Pub. L. 90–624, § 4(a)</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1968-10-22">Oct. 22, 1968</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/82/1316">82 Stat. 1316</ns0:ref>, as amended by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/99/514/s2">Pub. L. 99–514, § 2</ns0:ref>, <ns0:date date="1986-10-22">Oct. 22, 1986</ns0:date>, <ns0:ref href="/us/stat/100/2095">100 Stat. 2095</ns0:ref>, provided that:<ns0:quotedContent origin="/us/pl/99/514/s2">
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="1">“(1)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> The amendments made by the first two sections of this Act [amending this section and <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s228a">section 228a of Title 45</ns0:ref>, Railroads] shall apply with respect to service performed after <ns0:date date="1961-12-31">December 31, 1961</ns0:date>.</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="2">“(2)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> Notwithstanding the expiration before the date of the enactment of this Act [<ns0:date date="1968-10-22">Oct. 22, 1968</ns0:date>] or within 6 months after such date of the period for filing claim for credit or refund, claim for credit or refund of any overpayment of any tax imposed by chapter 22 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 [formerly I.R.C. 1954, <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3201">26 U.S.C. 3201</ns0:ref> et seq.] attributable to the amendment made by the first section of this Act [amending this section] may be filed at any time within one year after such date of enactment.</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
              <ns0:paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">
                <ns0:num value="3">“(3)</ns0:num>
                <ns0:content> Any credit or refund of an overpayment of the tax imposed by section 3201 or 3211 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 which is attributable to the amendment made by the first section of this Act shall be appropriately adjusted for any lump-sum payment which has been made under section 5(f)(2) of the Railroad Retirement Act of 1937 [<ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t45/s228e/f/2">section 228e(f)(2) of Title 45</ns0:ref>] before the date of the allowance of such credit or the making of such refund.”</ns0:content>
              </ns0:paragraph>
            </ns0:quotedContent>
          </ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687d2-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1965 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/89/212">Pub. L. 89–212</ns0:ref> effective only with respect to tips received after 1965, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/89/212/s6">section 6 of Pub. L. 89–212</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3201">section 3201 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDateOfAmendment" id="id457687d3-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date of 1954 Amendment</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">Amendment by act <ns0:date date="1954-08-31">Aug. 31, 1954</ns0:date>, effective as if enacted as a part of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 [formerly I.R.C. 1954], see section 407 of act <ns0:date date="1954-08-31">Aug. 31, 1954</ns0:date>, as amended, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3201">section 3201 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="miscellaneous" id="id457687d4-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Regulations</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">For provisions requiring that the regulations prescribed under subsec. (e)(4) of this section prescribe procedures under which, if (with respect to any employee) the third party promptly (A) withholds the employee portion of the taxes involved, (B) deposits such portion under section 6302 of such Code, and (C) notifies the employer of the amount of the wages or compensation involved, the employer (and not the third party) shall be liable for the employer portion of the taxes involved and for meeting the requirements of <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s6051">section 6051 of this title</ns0:ref> (relating to receipts for employees) with respect to the wages or compensation involved, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/123/s3/d">section 3(d) of Pub. L. 97–123</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3121">section 3121 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="miscellaneous" id="id457687d5-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Exclusion From Wages and Compensation of Refunds Required From Employers To Compensate for Duplication of Medicare Benefits by Health Care Benefits Provided by Employers</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">For purposes of this chapter, the term “compensation” shall not include the amount of any refund required under <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/100/360/s421">section 421 of Pub. L. 100–360</ns0:ref>, <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t42/s1395b">42 U.S.C. 1395b</ns0:ref> note, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/101/239/s10202">section 10202 of Pub. L. 101–239</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t42/s1395b">section 1395b of Title 42</ns0:ref>, The Public Health and Welfare.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
        <ns0:note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="miscellaneous" id="id457687d6-3a70-11f1-a967-d35dac11796a">
          <ns0:heading class="centered smallCaps">Payments Under State Temporary Disability Law To Be Treated as Remuneration for Service</ns0:heading>
          <ns0:p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0">For purposes of applying subsec. (e) of this section with respect to subsec. (e)(4) of this section, payments under a State temporary disability law to be treated as remuneration for service, see <ns0:ref href="/us/pl/97/123/s3/e">section 3(e) of Pub. L. 97–123</ns0:ref>, set out as a note under <ns0:ref href="/us/usc/t26/s3121">section 3121 of this title</ns0:ref>.</ns0:p>
        </ns0:note>
      </ns0:notes>
    </ns0:section>
  </ns0:title>
</ns0:uscDoc>