<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DIV5 N="247" TYPE="PART" VOLUME="4" hierarchy_metadata="{&amp;quot;path&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/part-247&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;citation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;7 CFR Part 247&amp;quot;}">
<HEAD>PART 247&#x2014;COMMODITY SUPPLEMENTAL FOOD PROGRAM
</HEAD>
<AUTH>
<HED>Authority:</HED><PSPACE>Sec. 5, Pub. L. 93-86, 87 Stat. 249, as added by Sec. 1304(b)(2), Pub. L. 95-113, 91 Stat. 980 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 1335, Pub. L. 97-98, 95 Stat. 1293 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 209, Pub. L. 98-8, 97 Stat. 35 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 2(8), Pub. L. 98-92, 97 Stat. 611 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 1562, Pub. L. 99-198, 99 Stat. 1590 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 101(k), Pub. L. 100-202; sec. 1771(a), Pub. L. 101-624, 101 Stat. 3806 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec 402(a), Pub. L. 104-127, 110 Stat. 1028 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 4201, Pub. L. 107-171, 116 Stat. 134 (7 U.S.C. 7901 note); sec. 4221, Pub. L. 110-246, 122 Stat. 1886 (7 U.S.C. 612c note); sec. 4221, Pub. L. 113-79, 7 U.S.C. 612c note).
</PSPACE></AUTH>
<SOURCE>
<HED>Source:</HED><PSPACE>70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, unless otherwise noted.
</PSPACE></SOURCE>
<EDNOTE>
<HED>Editorial Note:</HED><PSPACE>Nomenclature changes to part 247 appear at 89 FR 87228, Oct. 31, 2024.</PSPACE></EDNOTE>
<DIV8 N="247.1" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.1&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.1&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.1 Definitions.</HEAD>
<P>Following is a list of definitions that apply to the Commodity Supplemental Food Program (CSFP).</P>
<P><I>2 CFR part 200,</I> means the Uniform Administrative Requirements, Cost Principles, and Audit Requirements for Federal Awards published by OMB. The part reference covers applicable: Acronyms and Definitions (subpart A), General Provisions (subpart B), Post Federal Award Requirements (subpart D), Cost Principles (subpart E), and Audit Requirements (subpart F). (NOTE: Pre-Federal Award Requirements and Contents of Federal Awards (subpart C) does not apply to the National School Lunch Program).</P>
<P><I>Applicant</I> means any person who applies to receive program benefits. Applicants include program participants applying for recertification.</P>
<P><I>Caseload</I> means the number of persons the State agency may serve on an average monthly basis over the course of the caseload cycle.</P>
<P><I>Caseload cycle</I> means the period from January 1 through the following December 31.</P>
<P><I>Certification</I> means the use of procedures to determine an applicant's eligibility for the program.</P>
<P><I>Certification period</I> means the period during which a CSFP participant may continue to receive benefits under CSFP without a formal review of eligibility.</P>
<P><I>CSFP</I> means the Commodity Supplemental Food Program.</P>
<P><I>Department</I> means the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</P>
<P><I>Disqualification</I> means the act of ending Program participation of a participant as a punitive sanction.</P>
<P><I>Dual participation</I> means the simultaneous participation by an individual in CSFP at more than one distribution site.</P>
<P><I>Fiscal year</I> means the period from October 1 through the following September 30.</P>
<P><I>FNS</I> means the Food and Nutrition Service.</P>
<P><I>Local agency</I> means a public or private nonprofit agency, including an Indian tribal organization, which enters into an agreement with the State agency to administer CSFP at the local level.</P>
<P><I>Nonprofit agency</I> means a private agency or organization with tax-exempt status under the Internal Revenue Code, or that has applied for tax-exempt status with the Internal Revenue Service.</P>
<P><I>Proxy</I> means any person designated by a participant or caretaker to obtain USDA Foods on behalf of the participant.</P>
<P><I>7 CFR part 250</I> means the Department's regulations pertaining to the donation of foods for use in USDA food distribution programs.</P>
<P><I>State</I> means any of the 50 States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, and the Northern Mariana Islands.</P>
<P><I>State agency</I> means the agency designated by the State to administer CSFP at the State level; an Indian tribe or tribal organization recognized by the Department of the Interior that administers the program for a specified tribe or tribes; or, the appropriate area office of the Indian Health Service of the Department of Health and Human Services.</P>
<P><I>State Plan</I> means the document that describes the manner in which the State agency intends to administer the program in the State.</P>
<P><I>Subdistributing agency</I> means an agency or organization that has entered into an agreement with the State agency to perform functions normally performed by the State, such as entering into agreements with eligible recipient agencies under which USDA Foods are made available, ordering USDA Foods and/or making arrangements for the storage and delivery of such USDA Foods on behalf of eligible recipient agencies.</P>
<P><I>USDA Foods</I> means nutritious foods purchased by USDA to supplement the diets of CSFP participants, also referred to as donated foods.</P>
<P><I>USDA implementing regulations</I> include the following: 2 CFR part 400, Uniform Administrative Requirements, Cost Principles, and Audit Requirements for Federal Awards; 2 CFR part 415, General Program Administrative Regulations; 2 CFR part 416, General Program Administrative Regulations for Grants and Cooperative Agreements to State and Local Governments; and 2 CFR part 418, New Restrictions on Lobbying.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 81 FR 66495, Sept. 28, 2016; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020, 89 FR 87244, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.2" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.2&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.2&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.2 The purpose and scope of CSFP.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>How does CSFP help participants?</I> Through CSFP, the Department provides nutritious USDA Foods to help State and local agencies meet the nutritional needs of low-income participants. Food packages include such nutritious foods as canned fruits and vegetables, canned meat, poultry and other protein items, and grain products such as pasta, as well as other foods. Participants are offered the opportunity to receive nutrition education.</P>
<P>(b) <I>How many persons may be served in CSFP?</I> State agencies may serve eligible persons up to the caseload limit assigned to them by FNS. Caseload is the number of persons that may be served on an average monthly basis over the course of the caseload cycle, which extends from January 1 through the following December 31.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38750, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87244, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.3" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.3&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.3&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.3 Administering agencies.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What agencies are responsible for administering CSFP?</I> CSFP is administered at the Federal level by the Department's Food and Nutrition Service (FNS), which provides USDA Foods, assigns caseload, and allocates administrative funds to State agencies. State agencies are responsible for administering the program at the State level. The State agency may select local agencies to administer the program in local areas of the State. The State agency must provide guidance to local agencies on all aspects of program operations. The State agency may also select subdistributing agencies (e.g., another State agency, a local governmental agency, or a nonprofit organization) to distribute or store USDA Foods, or to perform other program functions on behalf of the State agency. Local or subdistributing agencies may also select other agencies to perform specific program functions (e.g., food distribution or storage), with the State agency's approval. Although the State agency may select other organizations to perform specific activities, the State agency is ultimately responsible for all aspects of program administration.</P>
<P>(b) <I>Are there specific functions that the State agency cannot delegate to another agency?</I> Yes. The State agency may not delegate the performance of the following functions to another agency:</P>
<P>(1) Establishing eligibility requirements, in accordance with the options provided to the State agency under &#xA7; 247.9; or</P>
<P>(2) Establishing a management review system and conducting reviews of local agencies, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.34.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What Federal requirements must State, subdistributing, and local agencies follow in administering CSFP?</I> State, subdistributing, and local agencies must administer the program in accordance with the provisions of this part, and with the provisions contained in part 250 of this chapter, unless they are inconsistent with the provisions of this part.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 89 FR 87244, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.4" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.4&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.4&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.4 Agreements.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What agreements are necessary for agencies to administer CSFP?</I> The following agreements are necessary for agencies to administer CSFP:</P>
<P>(1) <I>Agreements between FNS and State agencies.</I> Each State agency must enter into an agreement with FNS (Form FNS-74, the Federal-State Agreement) prior to receiving USDA Foods or administrative funds;</P>
<P>(2) <I>Agreements between State agencies and local or subdistributing agencies.</I> The State agency must enter into written agreements with local or subdistributing agencies prior to making USDA Foods or administrative funds available to them. The agreements must contain the information specified in paragraph (b) of this section. Agreements between State and local agencies must also contain the information specified in paragraph (c) of this section. Copies of all agreements must be kept on file by the parties to the agreements; and</P>
<P>(3) <I>Agreements between local and subdistributing agencies and other agencies.</I> The State agency must ensure that local and subdistributing agencies enter into written agreements with other agencies prior to making USDA Foods or administrative funds available to these other agencies. The agreements must contain the information specified in paragraph (b) of this section. Copies of all agreements must be kept on file by the parties to the agreements.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the required contents of agreements?</I> All agreements described under paragraphs (a)(2) and (a)(3) of this section must contain the following:</P>
<P>(1) An assurance that each agency will administer the program in accordance with the provisions of this part and with the provisions of part 250 of this chapter, unless they are inconsistent with the provisions of this part;</P>
<P>(2) An assurance that each agency will maintain accurate and complete records for a period of three years from the close of the fiscal year to which they pertain, or longer if the records are related to unresolved claims actions, audits, or investigations;</P>
<P>(3) A statement that each agency receiving USDA Foods for distribution is responsible for any loss resulting from improper distribution, or improper storage, care, or handling of USDA Foods;</P>
<P>(4) A statement that each agency receiving program funds is responsible for any misuse of program funds;</P>
<P>(5) A description of the specific functions that the State, subdistributing, or local agency is delegating to another agency; and</P>
<P>(6) A statement specifying:</P>
<P>(i) That either party may terminate the agreement by written notice to the other; and</P>
<P>(ii) The minimum number of days of advance notice that must be given. (The advance notification period must be at least 30 days.)</P>
<P>(c) <I>What other assurances or information must be included in agreements between State and local agencies?</I> In addition to the requirements under paragraph (b) of this section, agreements between State and local agencies must contain the following:</P>
<P>(1) An assurance that the local agency will provide, or cause to be provided, nutrition education to participants, as required in &#xA7; 247.18;</P>
<P>(2) An assurance that the local agency will provide information to participants on other health, nutrition, and public assistance programs, and make referrals as appropriate, as required in &#xA7; 247.14;</P>
<P>(3) An assurance that the local agency will distribute USDA Foods in accordance with the approved food package guide rate;</P>
<P>(4) An assurance that the local agency will take steps to prevent and detect dual participation, as required in &#xA7; 247.19;</P>
<P>(5) The names and addresses of all certification, distribution, and storage sites under the jurisdiction of the local agency; and</P>
<P>(6) An assurance that the local agency will not subject any person to discrimination under the program on the grounds of race, color, national origin, age, sex, or disability.</P>
<P>(d) <I>What is the duration of required agreements?</I> Agreements between FNS and State agencies are considered permanent, but may be amended at the initiation of State agencies or at the request of FNS. All amendments must be approved by FNS. The State agency establishes the duration of agreements it signs with local agencies or subdistributing agencies. The State agency may establish, or permit the local or subdistributing agency to establish, the duration of agreements between local or subdistributing agencies and other agencies. However, State and local agencies must comply with the requirements in &#xA7; 250.4 of this chapter when entering into agreements with other entities.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control numbers 0584-0067, 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87244, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.5" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.5&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.5&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.5 State and local agency responsibilities.</HEAD>
<P>State and local agencies are responsible for administering the program in accordance with the provisions of this part, and with the provisions of part 250 of this chapter, as applicable. Although the State agency may delegate some responsibilities to another agency, the State agency is ultimately responsible for all aspects of program administration. The following is an outline of the major responsibilities of State and local agencies; it is not intended to be all-inclusive.</P>
<P>(a) <I>What are the major responsibilities shared by State and local agencies?</I> The major responsibilities shared by State and local agencies include:</P>
<P>(1) Entering into required agreements;</P>
<P>(2) Ordering USDA Foods for distribution;</P>
<P>(3) Storing and distributing USDA Foods;</P>
<P>(4) Establishing procedures for resolving complaints about USDA Foods;</P>
<P>(5) Complying with civil rights requirements;</P>
<P>(6) Maintaining accurate and complete records; and</P>
<P>(7) Conducting program outreach.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the major State agency responsibilities?</I> The major responsibilities of State agencies include:</P>
<P>(1) Completing and submitting the State Plan;</P>
<P>(2) Selecting local agencies to administer the program in local areas of the State;</P>
<P>(3) Determining caseload needs, and submitting caseload requests to FNS;</P>
<P>(4) Assigning caseload, and allocating administrative funds, to local agencies;</P>
<P>(5) Establishing eligibility requirements, in accordance with the options provided to the State agency under &#xA7; 247.9. (This function may not be delegated to another agency.);</P>
<P>(6) Establishing nutritional risk criteria and a residency requirement for participants, if such criteria are to be used;</P>
<P>(7) Establishing a financial management system that effectively accounts for funds received for program administration;</P>
<P>(8) Developing a plan for the detection and prevention of dual participation, in coordination with CSFP local agencies;</P>
<P>(9) Developing a plan for providing nutrition education to participants;</P>
<P>(10) Establishing appeals and fair hearing procedures for local agencies and program participants;</P>
<P>(11) Developing a management review system and conducting reviews of local agencies. (This function may not be delegated to another agency.);</P>
<P>(12) Determining and pursuing claims, and establishing standards for pursuit of claims against participants;</P>
<P>(13) Ensuring compliance with Federal audit requirements;</P>
<P>(14) Providing guidance to local agencies, as needed;</P>
<P>(15) Ensuring that program participation does not exceed the State agency's caseload allocation on an average monthly basis;</P>
<P>(16) Making publicly available a list of all CSFP local agencies on a publicly available internet web page. The State agency must post the name, address, and telephone number for each local agency. The list must be updated, at a minimum, on an annual basis; and</P>
<P>(17) Posting the State Plan that is currently in use on a publicly available internet web page.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What are the major local agency responsibilities?</I> The major local agency responsibilities include:</P>
<P>(1) Determining eligibility of applicants in accordance with eligibility criteria established by the State agency;</P>
<P>(2) Complying with fiscal and operational requirements established by the State agency;</P>
<P>(3) Ensuring that participation does not exceed the caseload assigned by the State agency;</P>
<P>(4) Issuing foods to participants in accordance with the established food package guide rates;</P>
<P>(5) Providing nutrition education and information on the availability of other nutrition and health assistance programs to participants;</P>
<P>(6) Informing applicants of their rights and responsibilities in the program;</P>
<P>(7) Meeting the special needs of homebound participants, to the extent possible; and</P>
<P>(8) Pursuing claims against participants.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38750, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87244, Oct. 31, 2024; 89 FR 104393, Dec. 23, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.6" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.6&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.6&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.6 State Plan.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What is the State Plan?</I> The State Plan is a document that describes how the State agency will operate CSFP and the caseload needed to serve eligible applicants. The State agency must submit the State Plan to FNS for approval. Once submitted and approved, the State Plan is considered permanent, with amendments submitted at the State agency's initiative, or at FNS request. All amendments are subject to FNS approval. The State Plan may be submitted in the format provided in FNS guidance, in an alternate format, or in combination with other documents required by Federal regulations. The State Plan must be signed by the State agency official responsible for program administration. A copy of the State Plan must be kept on file at the State agency and must also be posted on a publicly available internet web page for public inspection.</P>
<P>(b) <I>When must the State Plan be submitted?</I> The State Plan must be submitted by August 15 to take effect for the fiscal year beginning in the following October. FNS will provide notification of the approval or disapproval of the State Plan within 30 days of receipt, and will notify the State agency within 15 days of receipt if additional information is needed. Disapproval of the Plan will include a reason for the disapproval. Approval of the Plan is a prerequisite to the assignment of caseload and allocation of administrative funds, but does not ensure that caseload and funds will be provided.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What must be included in the State Plan?</I> The State Plan must include:</P>
<P>(1) The names and addresses of all local agencies and subdistributing agencies with which the State agency has entered into agreement;</P>
<P>(2) The income eligibility standards and the options to be used relating to income or other eligibility requirements, as provided under &#xA7; 247.9;</P>
<P>(3) The nutritional risk criteria to be used, if the State chooses to establish such criteria;</P>
<P>(4) A description of plans for serving participants and the caseload needed to serve them;</P>
<P>(5) A description of plans for conducting outreach to participants;</P>
<P>(6) A description of the system for storing and distributing USDA Foods;</P>
<P>(7) A description of plans for providing nutrition education to participants;</P>
<P>(8) A description of the means by which the State agency will detect and prevent dual participation;</P>
<P>(9) A description of the standards the State agency will use in determining if the pursuit of a claim against a participant is cost-effective;</P>
<P>(10) A description of the means by which the State will meet the needs of homebound participants;</P>
<P>(11) Copies of all agreements entered into by the State agency;</P>
<P>(12) The length of the State agency's certification period; and</P>
<P>(13) A description of the process in place to verify the identity of participants before receipt of USDA Foods.</P>
<P>(d) <I>When must the State agency submit amendments to the State Plan?</I> The State agency must submit amendments to FNS to reflect any changes in program operations or administration described in the State Plan, and to request additional caseload for the following caseload cycle. FNS may also require that the State Plan be amended to reflect changes in Federal law or policy. The State agency may submit amendments to the State Plan at any time during the fiscal year, for FNS approval. The amendments will take effect immediately upon approval, unless otherwise specified by FNS. If a State agency would like to receive additional caseload for the caseload cycle beginning the following January 1, it must submit an amendment to the Plan which conveys the request for additional caseload by November 5. The State agency must also describe in this submission any plans for serving participants at new sites. FNS action on the State agency's request for additional caseload is part of the caseload assignment process, as described under &#xA7; 247.21.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38750, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87245, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.7" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.7&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.7&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.7 Selection of local agencies.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>How does a local agency apply to participate in CSFP?</I> Local agencies wishing to participate in CSFP must submit a written application to the State agency. The application must describe how the local agency will operate the program and, for nonprofit agencies, must include the agency's tax-exempt status. To be eligible to participate in CSFP, a nonprofit agency must have tax-exempt status under the Internal Revenue Code (IRC), or have applied for tax-exempt status with the Internal Revenue Service (IRS), and be moving towards such status. Nonprofit agencies organized or operated exclusively for religious purposes are automatically tax-exempt under the IRC. Nonprofit agencies required to obtain tax-exempt status must provide documentation from the IRS that they have obtained such status, or have applied for it.</P>
<P>(b) <I>On what basis does the State agency make a decision on the local agency's application?</I> The State agency must approve or disapprove the local agency's application based on, at minimum, the following criteria:</P>
<P>(1) The ability of the local agency to operate the program in accordance with Federal and State requirements;</P>
<P>(2) The need for the program in the projected service area of the local agency;</P>
<P>(3) The resources available (caseload and funds) for initiating a program in the local area; and</P>
<P>(4) For nonprofit agencies, the tax-exempt status, with appropriate documentation.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What must the State agency do if a nonprofit agency approved for CSFP is subsequently denied tax-exempt status by the IRS, or does not obtain this status within a certain period of time?</I> In accordance with paragraph (a) of this section, the State agency may approve a nonprofit agency that has applied to the IRS for tax-exempt status, and is moving toward compliance with the requirements for recognition of tax-exempt status. However, if the IRS subsequently denies a participating agency's application for recognition of tax-exempt status, the agency must immediately notify the State agency of the denial. The State agency must terminate the agency's agreement and participation immediately upon notification. If documentation of recognition of tax-exempt status is not received within 180 days of the effective date of the agency's approval to participate in CSFP, the State agency must terminate the agency's participation until such time as recognition of tax-exempt status is obtained. However, the State agency may grant an extension of 90 days if the agency demonstrates that its inability to obtain tax-exempt status in the 180-day period is due to circumstances beyond its control.</P>
<P>(d) <I>How much time does the State agency have to make a decision on the local agency's application?</I> The State agency must inform the local agency of approval or denial of the application within 60 days of its receipt. If the application is denied, the State agency must provide a written explanation for the denial, along with notification of the local agency's right to appeal the decision, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.35. If the application is approved, the State and local agency must enter into an agreement in accordance with the requirements of &#xA7; 247.4.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.8" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.8&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.8&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.8 Individuals applying to participate in CSFP.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What information must individuals applying to participate in CSFP provide?</I> To apply for or to be recertified for CSFP benefits, the applicant or caretaker of the applicant must provide the following information on the application:</P>
<P>(1) Name and address, including some form of identification for each applicant;</P>
<P>(2) Household income;</P>
<P>(3) Household size; and</P>
<P>(4) Other information related to eligibility, such as age</P>
<P>(b) <I>What else is required on the application form?</I> The application form must include a nondiscrimination statement that informs the applicant that program standards are applied without discrimination by race, color, national origin, age, sex, or disability. After informing the applicant or caretaker of the applicant of his or her rights and responsibilities, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.12, the local agency must ensure that the applicant or caretaker signs the application form beneath the following pre-printed statement. The statement must be read by, or to, the applicant or caretaker before signing.</P>
<P>&#x201C;This application is being completed in connection with the receipt of Federal assistance. Program officials may verify information on this form. I am aware that deliberate misrepresentation may subject me to prosecution under applicable State and Federal statutes. I am also aware that I may not receive CSFP benefits at more than one CSFP site at the same time. Furthermore, I am aware that the information provided may be shared with other organizations to detect and prevent dual participation. I have been advised of my rights and obligations under the program. I certify that the information I have provided for my eligibility determination is correct to the best of my knowledge.</P>
<EXTRACT>
<P>I authorize the release of information provided on this application form to other organizations administering assistance programs for use in determining my eligibility for participation in other public assistance programs and for program outreach purposes. (Please indicate decision by placing a checkmark in the appropriate box.)</P>
<FP>YES [ ]
</FP>
<FP>NO [ ]&#x201D;</FP></EXTRACT>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38750, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.9" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.9&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.9&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.9 Eligibility requirements.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>Who is eligible for CSFP?</I> To be eligible for CSFP, individuals must be at least 60 years of age and meet the income eligibility requirements outlined in paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the income eligibility requirements for CSFP applicants?</I> The State agency must use a household income limit at or below 150 percent of the U.S. Federal Poverty Guidelines published annually by the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS). Participants in households with income at or below this level must be considered eligible for CSFP benefits (assuming they meet other requirements contained in this part). However, participants certified before September 17, 1986 (<I>i.e.,</I> under the three elderly pilot projects) must remain subject to the eligibility criteria in effect at the time of their certification.</P>
<P>(1) The State agency may accept as income-eligible for CSFP benefits any applicant that documents that they are certified as fully eligible for the following Federal programs: the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program, the Food Distribution Program on Indian Reservations, Supplemental Security Income (SSI), the Low Income Subsidy Program, or the Medicare Savings Programs.</P>
<P>(2) The State agency may accept, as evidence of income within the State agency's CSFP guidelines, documentation of the applicant's participation in State-administered programs not specified in this paragraph that routinely require documentation of income, provided that those programs have income eligibility guidelines at or below the State agency's CSFP threshold.</P>
<P>(3) Applicants who are adjunctively income eligible, as set forth in paragraphs (b)(1) and (2) of this section, shall not be subject to the income limits established under paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
<P>(c) <I>When must the State agency revise the CSFP income guidelines to reflect the annual adjustments of the U.S. Federal Poverty Guidelines?</I> Each year, FNS will notify State agencies, by memorandum, of adjusted income guidelines by household size at 150 percent and 100 percent of the U.S. Federal Poverty Guidelines published annually by HHS. The memorandum will reflect the annual adjustments to the U.S. Federal Poverty Guidelines issued by HHS. The State agency must implement the adjusted guidelines immediately upon receipt of the memorandum.</P>
<P>(d) <I>How is income defined and considered as it relates to CSFP eligibility?</I> (1) Income means gross income before deductions for such items as income taxes, employees' social security taxes, insurance premiums, and bonds.</P>
<P>(2) The State agency may exclude from consideration the following sources of income:</P>
<P>(i) Any basic allowance for housing received by military services personnel residing off military installations; and</P>
<P>(ii) The value of inkind housing and other inkind benefits.</P>
<P>(3) The State agency must exclude from consideration all income sources excluded by legislation. FNS will notify State agencies of forms of income excluded by statute through program policy memoranda. The income sources which must be excluded from consideration as income include, but are not limited to:</P>
<P>(i) Reimbursements from the Uniform Relocation Assistance and Real Property Acquisition Policies Act of 1970 (Pub. L. 91-646, sec. 216, 42 U.S.C. 4636);</P>
<P>(ii) Any payment to volunteers under Title I (VISTA and others) and Title II (RSVP, foster grandparents, and others) of the Domestic Volunteer Service Act of 1973 (Pub. L. 93-113, sec. 404(g), 42 U.S.C. 5044(g)) to the extent excluded by that Act;</P>
<P>(iii) Payment to volunteers under section 8(b)(1)(B) of the Small Business Act (SCORE and ACE) (Pub. L. 95-510, sec. 101, 15 U.S.C. 637(b)(1)(D));</P>
<P>(iv) Income derived from certain submarginal land of the United States which is held in trust for certain Indian Tribes (Pub. L. 94-114, sec. 6, 25 U.S.C. 459e);</P>
<P>(v) Payments received under the Job Training Partnership Act (Pub. L. 97-300, sec. 142(b), 29 U.S.C. 1552(b));</P>
<P>(vi) Income derived from the disposition of funds to the Grand River Band of Ottawa Indians (Pub. L. 94-540, sec. 6);</P>
<P>(vii) Payments received under the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act (Pub. L. 100-241, sec. 15, 43 U.S.C. 1626(c));</P>
<P>(viii) The value of assistance to children or their families under the National School Lunch Act, as amended (Pub. L. 94-105, sec. 9(d), 42 U.S.C. 1760(e)), the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (Pub. L. 89-642, sec. 11(b), 42 U.S.C. 1780(b)), and the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (Pub. L. 95-113, sec. 1301, 7 U.S.C. 2017(b));</P>
<P>(ix) Payments by the Indian Claims Commission to the Confederated Tribes and Bands of the Yakima Indian Nation or the Apache Tribe of the Mescalero Reservation (Pub. L. 95-433, sec. 2, 25 U.S.C. 609c-1);</P>
<P>(x) Payments to the Passamaquoddy Tribe and the Penobscot Nation or any of their members received pursuant to the Maine Indian Claims Settlement Act of 1980 (Pub. L. 96-420, sec. 6, 9(c), 25 U.S.C. 1725(i), 1728(c));</P>
<P>(xi) Payments under the Low-income Home Energy Assistance Act, as amended (Pub. L. 99-125, sec. 504(c), 42 U.S.C. 8624(f));</P>
<P>(xii) Student financial assistance received from any program funded in whole or part under Title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965, including the Pell Grant, Supplemental Educational Opportunity Grant, State Student Incentive Grants, National Direct Student Loan, PLUS, College Work Study, and Byrd Honor Scholarship programs, which is used for costs described in section 472(1) and (2) of that Act (Pub. L. 99-498, section 479B, 20 U.S.C. 1087uu). The specified costs set forth in section 472(1) and (2) of the Higher Education Act are tuition and fees normally assessed a student carrying the same academic workload as determined by the institution, and including the costs for rental or purchase of any equipment, materials, or supplies required of all students in the same course of study; and an allowance for books, supplies, transportation, and miscellaneous personal expenses for a student attending the institution on at least a half-time basis, as determined by the institution. The specified costs set forth in section 472(1) and (2) of the Act are those costs which are related to the costs of attendance at the educational institution and do not include room and board and dependent care expenses;</P>
<P>(xiii) Payments under the Disaster Relief Act of 1974, as amended by the Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Amendments of 1989 (Pub. L. 100-707, sec. 105(i), 42 U.S.C. 5155(d));</P>
<P>(xiv) Effective July 1, 1991, payments received under the Carl D. Perkins Vocational Education Act, as amended by the Carl D. Perkins Vocational and Applied Technology Education Act Amendments of 1990 (Pub. L. 101-392, sec. 501, 20 U.S.C. 2466d);</P>
<P>(xv) Payments pursuant to the Agent Orange Compensation Exclusion Act (Pub. L. 101-201, sec. 1);</P>
<P>(xvi) Payments received for Wartime Relocation of Civilians under the Civil Liberties Act of 1988 (Pub. L. 100-383, sec. 105(f)(2), 50 App. U.S.C. 1989b-4(f)(2));</P>
<P>(xvii) Value of any child care payments made under section 402(g)(1)(E) of the Social Security Act, as amended by the Family Support Act (Pub. L. 100-485, sec. 301, 42 U.S.C. 602 (g)(1)(E));</P>
<P>(xviii) Value of any &#x201C;at-risk&#x201D; block grant child care payments made under section 5081 of Pub. L. 101-508, which amended section 402(i) of the Social Security Act;</P>
<P>(xix) Value of any child care provided or paid for under the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act, as amended (Pub. L. 102-586, Sec. 8(b)), 42 U.S.C. 9858q);</P>
<P>(xx) Mandatory salary reduction amount for military service personnel which is used to fund the Veteran's Educational Assistance Act of 1984 (GI Bill), as amended (Pub. L. 99-576, sec. 303(a)(1), 38 U.S.C. 1411 (b));</P>
<P>(xxi) Payments received under the Old Age Assistance Claims Settlement Act, except for per capita shares in excess of $2,000 (Pub. L. 98-500, sec. 8, 25 U.S.C. 2307);</P>
<P>(xxii) Payments received under the Cranston-Gonzales National Affordable Housing Act, unless the income of the family equals or exceeds 80 percent of the median income of the area (Pub. L. 101-625, sec. 522(i)(4), 42 U.S.C. 1437f nt);</P>
<P>(xxiii) Payments received under the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987, unless the income of the family increases at any time to not less than 50 percent of the median income of the area (Pub. L. 100-242, sec. 126(c)(5)(A), 25 U.S.C. 2307);</P>
<P>(xxiv) Payments received under the Sac and Fox Indian claims agreement (Pub. L. 94-189, sec. 6);</P>
<P>(xxv) Payments received under the Judgment Award Authorization Act, as amended (Pub. L. 97-458, sec. 4, 25 U.S.C. 1407 and Pub. L. 98-64, sec. 2(b), 25 U.S.C. 117b(b));</P>
<P>(xxvi) Payments for the relocation assistance of members of Navajo and Hopi Tribes (Pub. L. 93-531, sec. 22, 22 U.S.C. 640d-21);</P>
<P>(xxvii) Payments to the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewas, Arizona (Pub. L. 97-403, sec. 9);</P>
<P>(xxviii) Payments to the Blackfeet, Grosventre, and Assiniboine Tribes (Montana) and the Papago (Arizona) (Pub. L. 97-408, sec. 8(d));</P>
<P>(xxiv) Payments to the Assiniboine Tribe of the Fort Belknap Indian community and the Assiniboine Tribe of the Fort Peck Indian Reservation (Montana) (Pub. L. 98-124, sec. 5);</P>
<P>(xxx) Payments to the Red Lake Band of Chippewas (Pub. L. 98-123, sec. 3);</P>
<P>(xxxi) Payments received under the Saginaw Chippewa Indian Tribe of Michigan Distribution of Judgment Funds Act (Pub. L. 99-346, sec. 6(b)(2));</P>
<P>(xxxii) Payments to the Chippewas of Mississippi (Pub. L. 99-377, sec. 4(b));</P>
<P>(xxxiii) Payments received by members of the Armed Forces and their families under the Family Supplemental Subsistence Allowance from the Department of Defense (Pub. L. 109-163, sec. 608); and</P>
<P>(xxxiv) Payments received by property owners under the National Flood Insurance Program (Pub. L. 109-64).</P>
<P>(xxxv) Combat pay received by the household member under Chapter 5 of Title 37 or as otherwise designated by the Secretary.</P>
<P>(4) The State agency may authorize local agencies to consider the household's average income during the previous 12 months and current household income to determine which more accurately reflects the household's status. In instances in which the State makes the decision to authorize local agencies to determine a household's income in this manner, all local agencies must comply with the State's decision and apply this method of income determination in situations in which it is warranted.</P>
<P>(e) <I>What other options does the State agency have in establishing eligibility requirements for CSFP?</I> (1) The State agency may require that an individual be at nutritional risk, as determined by a physician or by local agency staff.</P>
<P>(2) The State agency may require that an individual reside within the service area of the local agency at the time of application for CSFP benefits. However, the State agency may not require that an individual reside within the area for any fixed period of time.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020, as amended at 89 FR 87245, Oct. 31, 2024; 89 FR 104393, Dec. 23, 2024]
</CITA>
<EDNOTE>
<HED>Editorial Note:</HED><PSPACE>At 89 FR 104393, Dec. 23, 2024, &#xA7; 247.9 was amended by correcting paragraph (d)(3)(xxiv); however, the amendment could not be incorporated due to inaccurate amendatory instruction.</PSPACE></EDNOTE>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.10" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.10&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.10&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.10 Distribution and use of USDA Foods.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are the requirements for distributing USDA Foods to participants?</I> The local agency must distribute a package of USDA Foods to participants each month, or a two-month supply of USDA Foods to participants every other month, in accordance with the food package guide rates established by FNS.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must the local agency do to ensure that USDA Foods are distributed only to CSFP participants?</I> The local agency must have a process in place, in accordance with State agency requirements, to verify the identity of participants or the participant's proxy before distributing USDA Foods to that person.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What restrictions apply to State and local agencies in the distribution of USDA Foods?</I> State and local agencies must not require, or request, that participants make any payments, or provide any materials or services, in connection with the receipt of USDA Foods. State and local agencies must not use the distribution of USDA Foods as a means of furthering the political interests of any person or party.</P>
<P>(d) <I>What are the restrictions for the use of USDA Foods?</I> USDA Foods may not be used for outreach, refreshments, or for any purposes other than distribution to, and nutrition education for, CSFP participants.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[89 FR 87246, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.11" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.11&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.11&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.11 Applicants exceed caseload levels.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What must the local agency do if the number of applicants exceeds the local agency's caseload level?</I> If all caseload has been filled, the local agency must maintain a waiting list of individuals who apply for the program. In establishing the waiting list, the local agency must include the date of application and information necessary to allow the local agency to contact the applicant when caseload space becomes available. Unless they have been determined ineligible, applicants must be notified of their placement on a waiting list within 10 days of their request for benefits in accordance with &#xA7; 247.15.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the requirements for serving individuals on the waiting list once caseload slots become available?</I> The local agency must certify eligible individuals from the waiting list consistent with civil rights requirements at &#xA7; 247.37. For example, a local agency may certify eligible individuals from the waiting list based on the date the application was received on a first-come, first-served basis.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 75 FR 5879, Feb. 5, 2010]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.12" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.12&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.12&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.12 Rights and responsibilities.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What information regarding an individual's rights in CSFP must the local agency provide to the applicant?</I> The local agency is responsible for informing the applicant, orally or in writing, of the following:</P>
<P>(1) The local agency will provide notification of a decision to deny or terminate CSFP benefits, and of an individual's right to appeal this decision by requesting a fair hearing, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.33(a);</P>
<P>(2) The local agency will make nutrition education available to all participants and will encourage them to participate; and</P>
<P>(3) The local agency will provide information on other nutrition, health, or assistance programs, and make referrals as appropriate.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What information regarding an individual's responsibilities in CSFP must the local agency provide to the applicant?</I> In addition to the written statement required by &#xA7; 247.8(b), the local agency is responsible for informing the applicant, orally or in writing, of the following:</P>
<P>(1) Improper use or receipt of CSFP benefits as a result of dual participation or other program violations may lead to a claim against the individual to recover the value of the benefits, and may lead to disqualification from CSFP; and</P>
<P>(2) Participants must report changes in household income or composition within 10 days after the change becomes known to the household.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.13" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.13&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.13&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.13 Provisions for non-English or limited-English speakers.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What must State and local agencies do to ensure that non-English or limited-English speaking persons are aware of their rights and responsibilities in the program?</I> If a significant proportion of the population in an area is comprised of non-English or limited-English speaking persons with a common language, the State agency must ensure that local agencies inform such persons of their rights and responsibilities in the program, as listed under &#xA7; 247.12, in an appropriate language. State and local agencies must ensure that bilingual staff members or interpreters are available to serve these persons.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must State and local agencies do to ensure that non-English or limited-English speaking persons are aware of other program information?</I> If a significant proportion of the population in an area is comprised of non-English or limited-English speaking persons with a common language, the State agency must ensure that local agencies provide other program information, except application forms, to such persons in their appropriate language.</P>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.14" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.14&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.14&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.14 Other public assistance programs.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What information on other public assistance programs must the local agency provide to applicants?</I> The local agency must provide applicants with written information on the following programs, and make referrals, as appropriate:</P>
<P>(1) Supplemental security income benefits provided under Title XVI of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1381 <I>et seq.</I>);</P>
<P>(2) Medical assistance provided under Title XIX of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1396 <I>et seq.</I>), including medical assistance provided to a qualified Medicare beneficiary (42 U.S.C. 1395(p) and 1396d(5));</P>
<P>(3) The Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program (7 U.S.C. 2011 <I>et seq.</I>); and</P>
<P>(4) The Senior Farmers' Market Nutrition Program (7 U.S.C. 3007 <I>et seq.</I>).</P>
<P>(b) <I>Is the value of CSFP benefits counted as income or resources for any other public assistance programs?</I> No. The value of benefits received in CSFP may not be considered as income or resources of participants or their families for any purpose under Federal, State, or local laws, including laws relating to taxation and public assistance programs.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68721, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87246, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.15" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.15&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.15&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.15 Notification of eligibility or ineligibility of applicant.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What is the timeframe for notifying an applicant of eligibility or ineligibility for CSFP benefits?</I> Local agencies must notify applicants of their eligibility or ineligibility for CSFP benefits, or their placement on a waiting list, within 10 days from the date of application.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must be included in the notification of eligibility or ineligibility?</I> The notification of eligibility must include information on the time, location, and means of food distribution, and the length of the certification period. Notification of ineligibility must be in writing, and must include the reason the applicant is not eligible, a statement of the individual's right to a fair hearing to appeal the decision, and a statement that informs the applicant that program standards are applied without discrimination by race, color, national origin, age, sex, or disability.</P>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.16" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.16&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.16&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.16 Certification period.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>How long is the certification period</I>&#x2014;(1) <I>Minimum certification period.</I> The State agency must establish certification periods that are not less than one year but not more than three years in duration. If the State agency chooses to establish a certification period that exceeds one year, the State must first receive approval from FNS by submitting a State Plan amendment. FNS shall approve State requests for a certification period exceeding one year on the condition that, on an annual basis, local agencies do the following:</P>
<P>(i) Verify the address and continued interest of the participant; and</P>
<P>(ii) Have sufficient reason to determine that the participant still meets the income eligibility standards, which may include a determination that the participant has a fixed income.</P>
<P>(2) <I>Temporary certification.</I> An eligible CSFP applicant, including individuals on waiting lists, may be provided with a temporary monthly certification to fill any caseload slot resulting from nonparticipation by certified participants.</P>
<P>(3) <I>Recertification.</I> Participants must be recertified following the application procedures outlined at &#xA7; 247.8 in order to continue receiving program benefits beyond the expiration of their certification period.</P>
<P>(b) <I>On what day of the final month does the certification period end?</I> The certification period extends to the final day of the month in which eligibility expires.</P>
<P>(c) <I>Does the certification period end when a participant moves from the local area in which he or she was receiving benefits?</I> No. The State agency must ensure that local agencies serve a CSFP participant who moves from another area to an area served by CSFP and whose certification period has not expired. The participant must be given the opportunity to continue to receive CSFP benefits for the duration of the certification period. If the local agency has a waiting list, the participant must be placed on its waiting list ahead of all other waiting applicants. The local agency that determined the participant's eligibility must provide verification of the expiration date of the certification period to the participant upon request.</P>
<P>(d) <I>What must the local agency do to ensure that participants are aware of the expiration of the certification period?</I> The local agency must notify program participants in writing at least 15 days before the expiration date that eligibility for the program is about to expire. The local agency must include a statement in the written notification that informs the applicant that program standards are applied without discrimination by race, color, national origin, age, sex, or disability.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 75 FR 5879, Feb. 5, 2010; 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68722, Oct. 30, 2020]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.17" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.17&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.17&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.17 Notification of discontinuance of participant.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What must a local agency do if it has evidence that a participant is no longer eligible for CSFP benefits during the certification period?</I> If a local agency has evidence that a participant is no longer eligible for CSFP benefits during the certification period, it must provide the participant with a written notification of discontinuance at least 15 days before the effective date of discontinuance.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must a local agency do if it has to discontinue a participant from participation in the program prior to the end of the certification period due to the lack of resources necessary to continue providing benefits to the participant?</I> If a local agency does not have sufficient resources, such as a sufficient number of caseload slots, to continue providing benefits to the participant(s) for the entire certification period, it must provide the participant(s) with a written notification of discontinuance at least 15 days before the effective date of discontinuance.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What must be included in the notification of discontinuance?</I> The notification of discontinuance must include the effective date of discontinuance, the reason for the participant's discontinuance, a statement of the individual's right to appeal the discontinuance through the fair hearing process, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.33(a), and a statement that informs the applicant that program standards are applied without discrimination by race, color, national origin, age, sex, or disability.</P>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.18" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.18&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.18&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.18 Nutrition education.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are the State agency's responsibilities in ensuring that nutrition education is provided?</I> The State agency must establish an overall nutrition education plan and must ensure that local agencies provide nutrition education to participants in accordance with the plan. The State agency may allow local agencies to share personnel and educational resources with other programs in order to provide the best nutrition education possible to participants. The State agency must establish an evaluation procedure to ensure that the nutrition education provided is effective. The evaluation procedure must include participant input and must be directed by a nutritionist or other qualified professional. The evaluation may be conducted by the State or local agency, or by another agency under agreement with the State or local agency.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What type of nutrition education must the local agency provide?</I> The local agency must provide nutrition education that can be easily understood by participants and is related to their nutritional needs and household situations. The local agency must provide nutrition education that includes the following information, which should account for specific ethnic and cultural characteristics whenever possible:</P>
<P>(1) The nutritional value of USDA Foods, and their relationship to the overall dietary needs of the population groups served;</P>
<P>(2) Nutritious ways to use USDA Foods;</P>
<P>(3) Special nutritional needs of participants and how these needs may be met;</P>
<P>(4) The importance of health care, and the role nutrition plays in maintaining good health; and</P>
<P>(5) The importance of the use of the foods by the participant to whom they are distributed, and not by another person.</P>
<P>(c) <I>To whom must local agencies provide nutrition education?</I> The local agency must make nutrition education available to all participants.</P>
<P>(d) <I>May USDA Foods be used in cooking demonstrations?</I> Yes. The State or local agency, or another agency with which it has signed an agreement, may use USDA Foods to conduct cooking demonstrations as part of the nutrition education provided to program participants, but not for other purposes.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68722, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87246, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.19" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.19&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.19&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.19 Dual participation.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What must State and local agencies do to prevent and detect dual participation?</I> The State agency must work with local agencies to prevent and detect dual participation. The State agency must work with local agencies to prevent and detect dual participation. In accordance with &#xA7; 247.8(a)(1), the local agency must check the identification of all applicants when they are certified or recertified. In accordance with &#xA7; 247.8(b), the local agency must ensure that the applicant or caretaker of the applicant signs an application form which includes a statement advising the applicant that he or she may not receive CSFP benefits at more than one CSFP site at the same time.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must the local agency do if a CSFP participant is found to be committing dual participation?</I> A participant found to be committing dual participation must be discontinued from participation at more than one CSFP site. In accordance with &#xA7; 247.20(b), if the dual participation resulted from the participant or caretaker of the participant making false or misleading statements, or intentionally withholding information, the local agency must disqualify the participant from CSFP, unless the local agency determines that disqualification would result in a serious health risk. The local agency must also initiate a claim against the participant to recover the value of CSFP benefits improperly received, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.30(c). Whenever an individual's participation in CSFP is discontinued, the local agency must notify the individual of the discontinuance, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.17. The individual may appeal the discontinuance through the fair hearing process, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.33(a).</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68722, Oct. 30, 2020]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.20" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.20&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.20&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.20 Program violations.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are program violations in CSFP?</I> Program violations are actions taken by CSFP applicants or participants, or caretakers of applicants or participants, to obtain or use CSFP benefits improperly. Program violations include the following actions:</P>
<P>(1) Intentionally making false or misleading statements, orally or in writing;</P>
<P>(2) Intentionally withholding information pertaining to eligibility in CSFP;</P>
<P>(3) Selling USDA Foods obtained in the program, or exchanging them for non-food items;</P>
<P>(4) Physical abuse, or threat of physical abuse, of program staff; or</P>
<P>(5) Committing dual participation.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the penalties for committing program violations?</I> If applicants or participants, or caretakers of applicants or participants, commit program violations, the State agency may require local agencies to disqualify the applicants or participants for a period of up to one year. However, if the local agency determines that disqualification would result in a serious health risk, the disqualification may be waived. For program violations that involve fraud, the State agency must require local agencies to disqualify the participant from CSFP for a period of up to one year, unless the local agency determines that disqualification would result in a serious health risk. The State agency must require local agencies to permanently disqualify a participant who commits three program violations that involve fraud. For purposes of this program, fraud includes:</P>
<P>(1) Intentionally making false or misleading statements to obtain USDA Foods;</P>
<P>(2) Intentionally withholding information to obtain USDA Foods; or</P>
<P>(3) Selling USDA Foods, or exchanging them for non-food items.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What must the local agency do to notify the individual of disqualification from CSFP?</I> The local agency must provide the individual with written notification of disqualification from CSFP at least 15 days before the effective date of disqualification. The notification must include the effective date and period of disqualification, the reason for the disqualification, and a statement that the individual may appeal the disqualification through the fair hearing process, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.33(a).</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 89 FR 87246, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.21" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.21&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.21&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.21 Caseload assignment.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>How does FNS assign caseload to State agencies?</I> Each year, FNS assigns a caseload to each State agency to allow persons meeting the eligibility criteria listed under &#xA7; 247.9 to participate in the program, up to the caseload limit. To the extent that resources are available, FNS assigns caseload to State agencies in the following order:</P>
<P>(1) <I>Base caseload.</I> The State agency may not receive base caseload in excess of its total caseload assigned for the previous caseload cycle. Base caseload is determined in the following manner:</P>
<P>(i) Each State agency entering its second year of program participation receives base caseload equal to the amount assigned to it in its first year of participation; and</P>
<P>(ii) A State agency that has participated in two or more caseload cycles receives base caseload equal to the highest of:</P>
<P>(A) Average monthly participation for the previous fiscal year; or</P>
<P>(B) Average monthly participation for the last quarter of the previous fiscal year; or</P>
<P>(C) Participation during September of the previous fiscal year, but only if:</P>
<P>(<I>1</I>) The full-year appropriation for the preceding fiscal year was enacted on or after February 15; and</P>
<P>(<I>2</I>) The State agency received additional caseload equal to or greater than 10 percent of its base caseload in the previous caseload cycle; and</P>
<P>(<I>3</I>) October participation in the current fiscal year was equal to or greater than 95 percent of September participation in the previous fiscal year.</P>
<P>(2) <I>Additional caseload.</I> Each participating State agency may request additional caseload to increase program participation. Eligibility for and assignment of additional caseload are determined in the following manner:</P>
<P>(i) A State agency entering its second year of program participation qualifies to receive additional caseload if the State achieved a participation level which was equal to or greater than 95 percent of assigned caseload for the previous caseload cycle, based on the highest of:</P>
<P>(A) Average monthly participation for the previous fiscal year; or</P>
<P>(B) Average monthly participation for the last quarter of the previous fiscal year; or</P>
<P>(C) Participation during September of the previous fiscal year, but only if:</P>
<P>(<I>1</I>) The full-year appropriation for the preceding fiscal year was enacted on or after February 15; and</P>
<P>(<I>2</I>) October participation in the current fiscal year was equal to or greater than 95 percent of September participation in the previous fiscal year.</P>
<P>(ii) A State agency that has participated in two or more caseload cycles qualifies to receive additional caseload if the State achieved a participation level which was equal to or greater than 95 percent of assigned caseload for the previous caseload cycle, based on the highest of:</P>
<P>(A) Average monthly participation for the previous fiscal year; or</P>
<P>(B) Average monthly participation for the last quarter of the previous fiscal year; or</P>
<P>(C) Participation during September of the previous fiscal year, but only if:</P>
<P>(<I>1</I>) The full-year appropriation for the preceding fiscal year was enacted on or after February 15; and</P>
<P>(<I>2</I>) The State agency received additional caseload equal to or greater than 10 percent of its base caseload in the previous caseload cycle; and</P>
<P>(<I>3</I>) October participation in the current fiscal year was equal to or greater than 95 percent of September participation in the previous fiscal year.</P>
<P>(iii) Of each eligible State agency's request for additional caseload, FNS assigns an amount that it determines the State needs and can efficiently utilize. In making this determination, FNS considers the factors listed below, in descending order of importance. If all reasonable requests for additional caseload cannot be met, FNS assigns it to those States that are most likely to utilize it. The factors are:</P>
<P>(A) The percentage of caseload utilized by the State in the previous fiscal year;</P>
<P>(B) Program participation trends in the State in previous fiscal years; and</P>
<P>(C) Other information provided by the State agency in support of the request.</P>
<P>(3) <I>New caseload.</I> Each State agency requesting to begin participation in the program, and with an approved State Plan, may receive caseload to serve participants, as requested in the State Plan. Of the State agency's caseload request, FNS assigns caseload in an amount that it determines the State needs and can efficiently utilize. This determination is made based on information contained in the State Plan and on other relevant information. However, if all caseload requests cannot be met, FNS will assign caseload to those States that are most likely to utilize it.</P>
<P>(b) <I>When does FNS assign caseload to State agencies?</I> FNS must assign caseload to State agencies by December 31 of each year, or within 30 days after enactment of appropriations legislation covering the full fiscal year, whichever comes later. Caseload assignments for the previous caseload cycle will remain in effect, subject to the availability of sufficient funding, until caseload assignments are made for the current caseload cycle.</P>
<P>(c) <I>How do State agencies request additional caseload for the next caseload cycle?</I> In accordance with &#xA7; 247.6(d), a State agency that would like additional caseload for the next caseload cycle (beginning the following January 1) must submit a request for additional caseload by November 5, as an amendment to the State Plan. The State agency must also describe plans for serving participants at new sites in this submission.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 75 FR 5879, Feb. 5, 2010; 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.22" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.22&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.22&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.22 Allocation and disbursement of administrative funds to State agencies.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What must State agencies do to be eligible to receive administrative funds?</I> In order to receive administrative funds, the State agency must have signed an agreement with FNS to operate the program, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.4(a)(1), and must have an approved State Plan.</P>
<P>(b) <I>How does FNS allocate administrative funds to State agencies?</I> (1) As required by law, each fiscal year FNS allocates to each State agency an administrative grant per assigned caseload slot, adjusted each year for inflation.</P>
<P>(2) For fiscal year 2003, the amount of the grant per assigned caseload slot was equal to the per-caseload slot amount provided in fiscal year 2001, adjusted by the percentage change between:</P>
<P>(i) The value of the State and local government price index, as published by the Bureau of Economic Analysis of the Department of Commerce, for the 12-month period ending June 30, 2001; and</P>
<P>(ii) The value of that index for the 12-month period ending June 30, 2002.</P>
<P>(3) For subsequent fiscal years, the amount of the grant per assigned caseload slot is equal to the amount of the grant per assigned caseload slot for the preceding fiscal year, adjusted by the percentage change between:</P>
<P>(i) The value of the State and local government price index, as published by the Bureau of Economic Analysis of the Department of Commerce, for the 12-month period ending June 30 of the second preceding fiscal year; and</P>
<P>(ii) The value of that index for the 12-month period ending June 30 of the preceding fiscal year.</P>
<P>(c) <I>How do State agencies access administrative funds?</I> FNS provides administrative funds to State agencies on a quarterly basis. Such funds are provided by means of a Letter of Credit, unless other funding arrangements have been made with FNS. The State agency obtains the funds by electronically accessing its Letter of Credit account.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.23" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.23&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.23&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.23 State provision of administrative funds to local agencies.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>How much of the administrative funds must State agencies provide to local agencies for their use?</I> The State agency must provide to local agencies for their use all administrative funds it receives, except that the State agency may retain for its own use the amount determined by the following formula:</P>
<P>(1) 15 percent of the first $50,000 received;</P>
<P>(2) 10 percent of the next $100,000 received;</P>
<P>(3) 5 percent of the next $250,000 received; and</P>
<P>(4) A maximum of $30,000, if the administrative grant exceeds $400,000.</P>
<P>(b) <I>May a State agency request to retain more than the amount determined by the above formula in the event of special needs?</I> Yes, the State agency may request approval from FNS to retain a larger amount than is allowed under the formula prescribed in paragraph (a) of this section. However, in making its request, the State agency must provide justification of the need for the larger amount at the State level, and must ensure that local agencies will not suffer undue hardship as a result of a reduction in administrative funds.</P>
<P>(c) <I>How must the State agency distribute funds among local agencies?</I> The State agency must distribute funds among local agencies on the basis of their respective needs, and in a manner that ensures the funds will be used to achieve program objectives.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.24" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.24&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.24&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.24 Recovery and redistribution of caseload and administrative funds.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>May FNS recover and redistribute caseload and administrative funds assigned to a State agency?</I> Yes. FNS may recover and redistribute caseload and administrative funds assigned to a State agency during the fiscal year. FNS will redistribute these resources to other State agencies in accordance with the provisions of &#xA7;&#xA7; 247.21(a) and 247.22(b). In reassigning caseload, FNS will use the most up-to-date data on participation and the extent to which caseload is being utilized, as well as other information provided by State agencies. In accordance with &#xA7; 247.21(a)(2), in instances in which FNS recovers caseload slots, the State agency must use 95 percent of its original caseload allocation to be eligible for additional caseload. However, the State agency must not exceed its reduced caseload allocation on an average monthly basis.</P>
<P>(b) <I>Is there a limit on the amount of caseload slots or administrative funds that FNS may recover?</I> Yes. FNS will not unilaterally recover caseload that would result in the recovery of more than 50 percent of the State's administrative funds. However, in instances in which the State agency requests that FNS recover any portion of its assigned caseload, the 50-percent limitation will not apply.</P>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.25" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.25&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.25&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.25 Allowable uses of administrative funds and other funds.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are allowable uses of administrative funds provided to State and local agencies?</I> Administrative funds may be used for costs that are necessary to ensure the efficient and effective administration of the program, in accordance with 2 CFR part 200, subpart E and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR part 400 and part 415, which set out the principles for determining whether specific costs are allowable. Some examples of allowable costs in CSFP include:</P>
<P>(1) Storing, transporting, and distributing foods;</P>
<P>(2) Determining the eligibility of program applicants;</P>
<P>(3) Program outreach;</P>
<P>(4) Nutrition education;</P>
<P>(5) Audits and fair hearings;</P>
<P>(6) Monitoring and review of program operations; and</P>
<P>(7) Transportation of participants to and from the local agency, if necessary.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are unallowable uses of administrative funds?</I> In addition to those costs determined to be unallowable by the principles contained in the OMB circulars referenced in paragraph (a) of this section, specific examples of unallowable uses of administrative funds in CSFP include:</P>
<P>(1) The cost of alteration of facilities not required specifically for the program; and</P>
<P>(2) Actual losses which could have been covered by permissible insurance (through an approved self-insurance program or by other means).</P>
<P>(c) <I>What costs are allowable only with prior approval of FNS?</I> Capital expenditures, which include the acquisition of facilities or equipment, or enhancements to such capital assets, with a cost per unit of at least $5,000, are allowable only with prior approval of FNS. Examples of equipment include automated information systems, automated data processing equipment, and other computer hardware and software.</P>
<P>(d) <I>What procedures must State and local agencies use in procuring property, equipment, or services with program funds, and disposing of such property or equipment?</I> The procedures that State and local agencies must follow in procuring property, equipment, or services with program funds, or disposing of such property or equipment, are contained in 2 CFR part 200, subpart E, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415, which set out the principles for determining whether specific costs are allowable. State, local, and Indian tribal governments must comply with 2 CFR part 200, subpart E, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415, while nonprofit subgrantees must comply with 2 CFR part 200, subpart E, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415. State and local agencies may use procurement procedures established by State and local regulations as long as these procedures do not conflict with Federal regulations. Federal regulations do not relieve State or local agencies from responsibilities established in contracts relating to procurement of property, equipment, or services. The State agency is the responsible authority regarding the settlement of all contractual and administrative issues arising out of procurements for the program.</P>
<P>(e) <I>What is program income and how must State and local agencies use it?</I> Program income is income directly generated from program activities. It includes, for example, income from the sale of packing containers or pallets, and the salvage of USDA Foods. Program income does not include interest earned from administrative funds. State and local agencies must use program income for allowable program costs, in accordance with 2 CFR part 200, subpart E, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415.</P>
<P>(f) <I>How must State and local agencies use funds recovered as a result of claims actions?</I> The State agency must use funds recovered as a result of claims actions against subdistributing or local agencies in accordance with the provisions of &#xA7; 250.17(c) of this chapter. The State agency must use funds recovered as a result of claims actions against participants for allowable program costs. The State agency may authorize local agencies to use such funds for allowable program costs incurred at the local level.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 81 FR 66496, Sept. 28, 2016; 83 FR 14173, Apr. 3, 2018; 85 FR 68722, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.26" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.26&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.26&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.26 Return of administrative funds.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>Must State agencies return administrative funds that they do not use at the end of the fiscal year?</I> Yes. If, by the end of the fiscal year, a State agency has not obligated all of its allocated administrative funds, the unobligated funds must be returned to FNS.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What happens to administrative funds that are returned by State agencies at the end of the fiscal year?</I> If, in the following fiscal year, OMB reapportions the returned administrative funds, the funds are used to support the program. Such funds are not returned to State agencies in the form of administrative funds in addition to the legislatively mandated grant per assigned caseload slot.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.27" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.27&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.27&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.27 Financial management.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are the Federal requirements for State and local agencies with regard to financial management?</I> State and local public agencies, as well as nonprofit organizations, must maintain a financial management system that complies with the Federal regulations contained in 2 CFR part 200, subparts D and E, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415. The State agency's financial management system must provide accurate, current, and complete disclosure of the financial status of the program, including an accounting of all program funds received and expended each fiscal year. The State agency must ensure that local agencies develop and implement a financial management system that allows them to meet Federal requirements.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are some of the major components of the State agency's financial management system?</I> In addition to other requirements, the State agency's financial management system must provide for:</P>
<P>(1) Prompt and accurate payment of allowable costs;</P>
<P>(2) Timely disbursement of funds to local agencies;</P>
<P>(3) Timely and appropriate resolution of claims and audit findings; and</P>
<P>(4) Maintenance of records identifying the receipt and use of administrative funds, funds recovered as a result of claims actions, program income (as defined under &#xA7; 247.25(e)), and property and other assets procured with program funds.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 83 FR 14174, Apr. 3, 2018]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.28" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.28&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.28&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.28 Storage and inventory of USDA Foods.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are the requirements for storage of USDA Foods?</I> State and local agencies must provide for storage of USDA Foods that protects them from theft, spoilage, damage or destruction, or other loss. State and local agencies may contract with commercial facilities to store and distribute USDA Foods. The required standards for warehousing and distribution systems, and for contracts with storage facilities, are included in &#xA7;&#xA7; 250.12 and 250.14 of this chapter.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the requirements for the inventory of USDA Foods?</I> A physical inventory of all USDA Foods must be conducted annually at each storage and distribution site where these USDA Foods are stored. Results of the physical inventory must be reconciled with inventory records and maintained on file by the State or local agency.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.29" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.29&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.29&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.29 Reports and recordkeeping.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What recordkeeping requirements must State and local agencies meet?</I> State and local agencies must maintain accurate and complete records relating to the receipt, disposal, and inventory of USDA Foods, the receipt and disbursement of administrative funds and other funds, eligibility determinations, fair hearings, and other program activities. State and local agencies must also maintain records pertaining to liability for any improper distribution of, use of, loss of, or damage to USDA Foods, and the results obtained from the pursuit of claims arising in favor of the State or local agency. All records must be retained for a period of three years from the end of the fiscal year to which they pertain, or, if they are related to unresolved claims actions, audits, or investigations, until those activities have been resolved. All records must be available during normal business hours for use in management reviews, audits, investigations, or reports of the General Accounting Office.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What reports must State and local agencies submit to FNS?</I> State agencies must submit the following reports to FNS:</P>
<P>(1) <I>SF-425, Federal Financial Report.</I> The State agency must submit the SF-425, Federal Financial Report, to report the financial status of the program at the close of the fiscal year. This report must be submitted within 90 days after the end of the fiscal year. Obligations must be reported for the fiscal year in which they occur. Revised reports may be submitted at a later date, but FNS will not be responsible for reimbursing unpaid obligations later than one year after the end of the fiscal year in which they were incurred.</P>
<P>(2) <I>FNS-153, Monthly Report of the Commodity Supplemental Food Program and Quarterly Administrative Financial Status Report.</I> The State agency must submit the FNS-153 on a monthly basis. FNS may permit the data contained in the report to be submitted less frequently, or in another format. The report must be submitted within 30 days after the end of the reporting period. On the FNS-153, the State agency reports:</P>
<P>(i) The number of program participants;</P>
<P>(ii) The receipt and distribution of USDA Foods, and beginning and ending inventories, as well as other USDA Foods data; and</P>
<P>(iii) On a quarterly basis, the cumulative amount of administrative funds expended and obligated, and the amount remaining unobligated.</P>
<P>(3) <I>FNS-191, Racial/Ethnic Group Participation.</I> Local agencies must submit a report of racial/ethnic participation each year, using the FNS-191.</P>
<P>(c) <I>Is there any other information that State and local agencies must provide to FNS?</I> FNS may require State and local agencies to provide data collected in the program to aid in the evaluation of the effect of program benefits on the low-income populations served. Any such requests for data will not include identification of particular individuals.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control numbers 0584-0025, 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 72 FR 24184, May 2, 2007; 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68722, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.30" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.30&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.30&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.30 Claims.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What happens if a State or local agency misuses program funds?</I> If FNS determines that a State or local agency has misused program funds through negligence, fraud, theft, embezzlement, or other causes, FNS must initiate and pursue a claim against the State agency to repay the amount of the misused funds. The State agency will be given the opportunity to contest the claim. The State agency is responsible for initiating and pursuing claims against subdistributing and local agencies if they misuse program funds.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What happens if a State or local agency misuses USDA Foods?</I> If a State or local agency misuses USDA Foods, FNS must initiate a claim against the State agency to recover the value of the misused USDA Foods. The procedures for pursuing claims resulting from misuse of USDA Foods are detailed in &#xA7; 250.16(a) of this chapter. Misused USDA Foods include USDA Foods improperly distributed or lost, spoiled, stolen, or damaged as a result of improper storage, care, or handling. The State agency is responsible for initiating and pursuing claims against subdistributing agencies, local agencies, or other agencies or organizations if they misuse USDA Foods. The State agency must use funds recovered as a result of claims for USDA Foods losses in accordance with &#xA7; 250.17(c) of this chapter.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What happens if a participant improperly receives or uses CSFP benefits through fraud?</I> The State agency must ensure that a local agency initiates a claim against a participant to recover the value of USDA Foods improperly received or used if the local agency determines that the participant or caretaker of the participant fraudulently received or used the USDA Foods. For purposes of this program, fraud includes intentionally making false or misleading statements, or intentionally withholding information, to obtain USDA Foods, or the selling or exchange of USDA Foods for non-food items. The local agency must advise the participant of the opportunity to appeal the claim through the fair hearing process, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.33(a). The local agency must also disqualify the participant from CSFP for a period of up to one year, unless the local agency determines that disqualification would result in a serious health risk, in accordance with the requirements of &#xA7; 247.20(b).</P>
<P>(d) <I>What procedures must be used in pursuing claims against participants?</I> The State agency must establish standards, based on a cost-benefit review, for determining when the pursuit of a claim is cost-effective, and must ensure that local agencies use these standards in determining if a claim is to be pursued. In pursuing a claim against a participant, the local agency must:</P>
<P>(1) Issue a letter demanding repayment for the value of the USDA Foods improperly received or used;</P>
<P>(2) If repayment is not made in a timely manner, take additional collection actions that are cost-effective, in accordance with the standards established by the State agency; and</P>
<P>(3) Maintain all records regarding claims actions taken against participants, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.29.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 85 FR 68722, Oct. 30, 2020; 89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.31" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.31&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.31&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.31 Audits and investigations.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What is the purpose of an audit?</I> The purpose of an audit is to ensure that:</P>
<P>(1) Financial operations are properly conducted;</P>
<P>(2) Financial reports are fairly presented;</P>
<P>(3) Proper inventory controls are maintained; and</P>
<P>(4) Applicable laws, regulations, and administrative requirements are followed.</P>
<P>(b) <I>When may the Department conduct an audit or investigation of the program?</I> The Department may conduct an audit of the program at the State or local agency level at its discretion, or may investigate an allegation that the State or local agency has not complied with Federal requirements. An investigation may include a review of any State or local agency policies or practices related to the specific area of concern.</P>
<P>(c) <I>What are the responsibilities of the State agency in responding to an audit by the Department?</I> In responding to an audit by the Department, the State agency must:</P>
<P>(1) Provide access to any records or documents compiled by the State or local agencies, or contractors; and</P>
<P>(2) Submit a response or statement to FNS describing the actions planned or taken in response to audit findings or recommendations. The corrective action plan must include time frames for implementation and completion of actions. FNS will determine if actions or planned actions adequately respond to the program deficiencies identified in the audit. If additional actions are needed, FNS will schedule a follow-up review and allow sufficient time for further corrective actions. The State agency may also take exception to particular audit findings or recommendations.</P>
<P>(d) <I>When is a State or local agency audit required?</I> State and local agency audits must be conducted in accordance with part 3052 of this title, which contains the Department's regulations pertaining to audits of States, local governments, and nonprofit organizations. The value of USDA Foods distributed by the agency or organization must be considered part of the Federal award.</P>
<P>(e) <I>What are the requirements for State or local agency audits?</I> State and local agency audits must be conducted in accordance with the requirements of part 3052 of this title, which contains the Department's regulations pertaining to audits of States, local governments, and nonprofit organizations. The State agency must ensure that local agencies meet the audit requirements. The State agency must ensure that all State or local agency audit reports are available for FNS review.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.32" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.32&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.32&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.32 Termination of agency participation.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>When may a State agency's participation in CSFP be terminated?</I> While paragraphs (a)(1), (a)(2), and (a)(3) of this section, as applicable, describe the circumstances and basic procedures for terminating State agency programs, specific actions and procedures relating to program termination are more fully described in 2 CFR part 200, subpart D, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415.</P>
<P>(1) <I>Termination by FNS.</I> FNS may terminate a State agency's participation in CSFP, in whole or in part, if the State agency does not comply with the requirements of this part. FNS must provide written notification to the State agency of termination, including the reasons for the action, and the effective date.</P>
<P>(2) <I>Termination by State agency.</I> The State agency may terminate the program, in whole or in part, upon written notification to FNS, stating the reasons and effective date of the action. In accordance with &#xA7; 247.4(b)(6), which relates to the termination of agreements, either party must provide, at minimum, 30 days' written notice.</P>
<P>(3) <I>Termination by mutual agreement.</I> The State agency's program may also be terminated, in whole or in part, if both parties agree the action would be in the best interest of the program. The two parties must agree upon the conditions of the termination, including the effective date.</P>
<P>(b) <I>When may a local agency's participation in CSFP be terminated?</I> While paragraphs (b)(1), (b)(2), and (b)(3) of this section, as applicable, describe the circumstances and basic procedures in termination of local agency programs, specific actions and procedures relating to program termination are more fully described in 2 CFR part 200, subpart D, and USDA implementing regulations 2 CFR parts 400 and 415.</P>
<P>(1) <I>Termination by State agency.</I> The State agency may terminate a local agency's participation in CSFP, or may be required to terminate a local agency's participation, in whole or in part, if the local agency does not comply with the requirements of this part. The State agency must notify the local agency in writing of the termination, the reasons for the action, and the effective date, and must provide the local agency with an opportunity to appeal, in accordance with &#xA7; 247.35. (The local agency may appeal the termination in accordance with &#xA7; 247.35.)</P>
<P>(2) <I>Termination by local agency.</I> The local agency may terminate the program, in whole or in part, upon written notification to the State agency, stating the reasons and effective date of the action. In accordance with &#xA7; 247.4(b)(6), which relates to the termination of agreements, either party must provide, at minimum, 30 days' written notice.</P>
<P>(3) <I>Termination by mutual agreement.</I> The local agency's program may also be terminated, in whole or in part, if both the State and local agency agree that the action would be in the best interest of the program. The two parties must agree upon the conditions of the termination, including the effective date.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 83 FR 14174, Apr. 3, 2018]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.33" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.33&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.33&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.33 Fair hearings.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What is a fair hearing?</I> A fair hearing is a process that allows a CSFP applicant or participant to appeal an adverse action, which may include the denial or discontinuance of program benefits, disqualification from the program, or a claim to repay the value of USDA Foods received as a result of fraud. State and local agencies must ensure that CSFP applicants and participants understand their right to appeal an adverse action through the fair hearing process, which includes providing written notification of the individual's right to a fair hearing along with notification of the adverse action. Such notification is not required at the expiration of a certification period.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What are the basic requirements the State agency must follow in establishing procedures to be used in fair hearings?</I> The State agency must establish simple, clear, uniform rules of procedure to be used in fair hearings, including, at a minimum, the procedures outlined in this section. The State agency may use alternate procedures if approved by FNS. The rules of procedure must be available for public inspection and copying.</P>
<P>(c) <I>How may an individual request a fair hearing?</I> An individual or an individual's caretaker may request a fair hearing by making a clear expression, verbal or written, to a State or local agency official that an appeal of the adverse action is desired.</P>
<P>(d) <I>How much time does an individual have to request a fair hearing?</I> The State or local agency must allow an individual at least 60 days from the date the agency mails or gives the individual the notification of adverse action to request a fair hearing.</P>
<P>(e) <I>When may a State or local agency deny a request for a fair hearing?</I> The State or local agency may deny a request for a fair hearing when:</P>
<P>(1) The request is not received within the time limit established in paragraph (d) of this section;</P>
<P>(2) The request is withdrawn in writing by the individual requesting the hearing or by an authorized representative of the individual; or</P>
<P>(3) The individual fails to appear, without good cause, for the scheduled hearing.</P>
<P>(f) <I>Does the request for a fair hearing have any effect on the receipt of CSFP benefits?</I> Participants who appeal the discontinuance of program benefits within the 15-day advance notification period required under &#xA7;&#xA7; 247.17 and 247.20 must be permitted to continue to receive benefits until a decision on the appeal is made by the hearing official, or until the end of the participant's certification period, whichever occurs first. However, if the hearing decision finds that a participant received program benefits fraudulently, the local agency must include the value of benefits received during the time that the hearing was pending, as well as for any previous period, in its initiation and pursuit of a claim against the participant.</P>
<P>(g) <I>What notification must the State or local agency provide an individual in scheduling the hearing?</I> The State or local agency must provide an individual with at least 10 days' advance written notice of the time and place of the hearing, and must include the rules of procedure for the hearing.</P>
<P>(h) <I>What are the individual's rights in the actual conduct of the hearing?</I> The individual must have the opportunity to:</P>
<P>(1) Examine documents supporting the State or local agency's decision before and during the hearing;</P>
<P>(2) Be assisted or represented by an attorney or other persons;</P>
<P>(3) Bring witnesses;</P>
<P>(4) Present arguments;</P>
<P>(5) Question or refute testimony or evidence, including an opportunity to confront and cross-examine others at the hearing; and,</P>
<P>(6) Submit evidence to help establish facts and circumstances.</P>
<P>(i) <I>Who is responsible for conducting the fair hearing, and what are the specific responsibilities of that person?</I> The fair hearing must be conducted by an impartial official who does not have any personal stake or involvement in the decision and who was not directly involved in the initial adverse action that resulted in the hearing. The hearing official is responsible for:</P>
<P>(1) Administering oaths or affirmations, as required by the State;</P>
<P>(2) Ensuring that all relevant issues are considered;</P>
<P>(3) Ensuring that all evidence necessary for a decision to be made is presented at the hearing, and included in the record of the hearing;</P>
<P>(4) Ensuring that the hearing is conducted in an orderly manner, in accordance with due process; and</P>
<P>(5) Making a hearing decision.</P>
<P>(j) <I>How is a hearing decision made?</I> The hearing official must make a decision that complies with Federal laws and regulations, and is based on the facts in the hearing record. In making the decision, the hearing official must summarize the facts of the case, specify the reasons for the decision, and identify the evidence supporting the decision and the laws or regulations that the decision upholds. The decision made by the hearing official is binding on the State or local agency.</P>
<P>(k) <I>What is the time limit for making a hearing decision and notifying the individual of the decision?</I> A hearing decision must be made, and the individual notified of the decision, in writing, within 45 days of the request for the hearing. The notification must include the reasons for the decision.</P>
<P>(l) <I>How does the hearing decision affect the individual's receipt of CSFP benefits?</I> If a hearing decision is in favor of an applicant who was denied CSFP benefits, the receipt of benefits must begin within 45 days from the date that the hearing was requested, if the applicant is still eligible for the program. If the hearing decision is against a participant, the State or local agency must discontinue benefits as soon as possible, or at a date determined by the hearing official.</P>
<P>(m) <I>What must be included in the hearing record?</I> In addition to the hearing decision, the hearing record must include a transcript or recording of testimony, or an official report of all that transpired at the hearing, along with all exhibits, papers, and requests made. The record must be maintained in accordance with &#xA7; 247.29(a). The record of the hearing must be available for public inspection and copying, in accordance with the confidentiality requirements under &#xA7; 247.36(b).</P>
<P>(n) <I>What further steps may an individual take if a hearing decision is not in his or her favor?</I> If a hearing decision upholds the State or local agency's action, and a State-level review or rehearing process is available, the State or local agency must describe to the individual any State-level review or rehearing process. The State or local agency must also inform the individual of the right of the individual to pursue judicial review of the decision.</P>
<CITA TYPE="N">[70 FR 47063, Aug. 11, 2005, as amended at 79 FR 38751, July 9, 2014; 89 FR 87247, Oct. 31, 2024]
</CITA>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.34" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.34&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.34&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.34 Management reviews.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What must the State agency do to ensure that local agencies meet program requirements and objectives?</I> The State agency must establish a management review system to ensure that local agencies, subdistributing agencies, and other agencies conducting program activities meet program requirements and objectives. As part of the system, the State agency must perform an on-site review of all local agencies, and of all storage facilities utilized by local agencies, at least once every two years. As part of the on-site review, the State agency must evaluate all aspects of program administration, including certification procedures, nutrition education, civil rights compliance, food storage practices, inventory controls, and financial management systems. In addition to conducting on-site reviews, the State agency must evaluate program administration on an ongoing basis by reviewing financial reports, audit reports, food orders, inventory reports, and other relevant information.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must the State agency do if it finds that a local agency is deficient in a particular area of program administration?</I> The State agency must record all deficiencies identified during the review and institute follow-up procedures to ensure that local agencies and subdistributing agencies correct all deficiencies within a reasonable period of time. To ensure improved program performance in the future, the State agency may require that local agencies adopt specific review procedures for use in reviewing their own operations and those of subsidiaries or contractors. The State agency must provide copies of review reports to FNS upon request.</P>
<APPRO TYPE="N">(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under control number 0584-0293)
</APPRO>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.35" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.35&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.35&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.35 Local agency appeals of State agency actions.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What recourse must the State agency provide local agencies to appeal a decision that adversely affects their participation in CSFP?</I> The State agency must establish a hearing procedure to allow local agencies to appeal a decision that adversely affects their participation in CSFP&#x2014;e.g., the termination of a local agency's participation in the program. The adverse action must be postponed until a decision on the appeal is made.</P>
<P>(b) <I>What must the State agency include in the hearing procedure to ensure that the local agency has a fair chance to present its case?</I> The hearing procedure must provide the local agency:</P>
<P>(1) Adequate advance notice of the time and place of the hearing;</P>
<P>(2) An opportunity to review the record before the hearing, and to present evidence at the hearing;</P>
<P>(3) An opportunity to confront and cross-examine witnesses; and</P>
<P>(4) An opportunity to be represented by counsel, if desired.</P>
<P>(c) <I>Who conducts the hearing and how is a decision on the appeal made?</I> The hearing must be conducted by an impartial person who must make a decision on the appeal that is based solely on the evidence presented at the hearing, and on program legislation and regulations. A decision must be made within 60 days from the date of the request for a hearing, and must be provided in writing to the local agency.</P>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.36" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.36&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.36&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.36 Confidentiality of applicants or participants.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>Can the State or local agency disclose information obtained from applicants or participants to other agencies or individuals?</I> State and local agencies must restrict the use or disclosure of information obtained from CSFP applicants or participants to persons directly connected with the administration or enforcement of the program, including persons investigating or prosecuting program violations. The State or local agency may exchange participant information with other health or welfare programs for the purpose of preventing dual participation. In addition, with the consent of the participant, as indicated on the application form, the State or local agency may share information obtained with other health or welfare programs for use in determining eligibility for those programs, or for program outreach. However, the State agency must sign an agreement with the administering agencies for these programs to ensure that the information will be used only for the specified purposes, and that agencies receiving such information will not further share it.</P>
<P>(b) <I>Can the State or local agency disclose the identity of persons making a complaint or allegation against another individual participating in or administering the program?</I> The State or local agency must protect the confidentiality, and other rights, of any person making allegations or complaints against another individual participating in, or administering CSFP, except as necessary to conduct an investigation, hearing, or judicial proceeding.</P>
</DIV8>

<DIV8 N="247.37" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-7/section-247.37&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;7 CFR 247.37&quot;}">
<HEAD>&#xA7; 247.37 Civil rights requirements.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>What are the civil rights requirements that apply to CSFP?</I> State and local agencies must comply with the requirements of Title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (42 U.S.C. 2000d <I>et seq.</I>), Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (20 U.S.C. 1681 <I>et seq.</I>), section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (29 U.S.C. 794 <I>et seq.</I>), the Age Discrimination Act of 1975 (42 U.S.C. 6101 <I>et seq.</I>), and titles II and III of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. 12101 <I>et seq.</I>). State and local agencies must also comply with the Department's regulations on nondiscrimination (parts 15, 15a, and 15b of this title), and with the provisions of FNS Instruction 113-2, including the collection of racial/ethnic participation data and public notification of nondiscrimination policy. State and local agencies must ensure that no person shall, on the grounds of race, color, national origin, age, sex, or disability, be subjected to discrimination under the program.</P>
<P>(b) <I>How does an applicant or participant file a complaint of discrimination?</I> CSFP applicants or participants who believe they have been discriminated against should file a discrimination complaint with the USDA Director, Office of Civil Rights, Room 326W, Whitten Building, 1400 Independence Avenue, SW., Washington, DC 20250-9410, or telephone (202) 720-5964.</P>
</DIV8>

</DIV5>
